<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glasse for good vvomen, held forth by way of counsell and advice to such of that sex and quality, as in the simplicity of their hearts, are led away to the imbracing or looking towards any of the dangerous errors of the times, specially that of the separation. / As it was lately presented to the Church of God at Great-Yarmouth, by John Brinsley. Octob. 9. 1645. Imprimatur Ja: Cranford.</title>
            <author>Brinsley, John, 1600-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E305_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200330</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861133</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861133</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 50:E305[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glasse for good vvomen, held forth by way of counsell and advice to such of that sex and quality, as in the simplicity of their hearts, are led away to the imbracing or looking towards any of the dangerous errors of the times, specially that of the separation. / As it was lately presented to the Church of God at Great-Yarmouth, by John Brinsley. Octob. 9. 1645. Imprimatur Ja: Cranford.</title>
                  <author>Brinsley, John, 1600-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Field for Ralph Smith, at the sign of the Bible in Cornhill, neer the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Separatists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113261:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113261:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LOOKING-GLASSE FOR GOOD WOMEN,</p>
            <p>Held forth by way of Counſell and Advice to ſuch of that Sex and Quality, as in the ſimplicity of their Hearts, are led away to the imbracing or looking towards any of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Errors of the Times, ſpecially that of the SEPARATION.</p>
            <p>As it was lately preſented to the Church of God at Great-YARMOUTH, BY JOHN BRINSLEY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 COR. 11.3.</bibl>
               <p>I fear leaſt as the Serpent beguiled Eve through his ſubtilty, ſo your mindes ſhould be corrupt from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Octob.</hi> 9. 1645.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>JA: CRANFORD.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Field</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the ſign of the Bible in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> neer the <hi>Royall Exchange,</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113261:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113261:2"/>
            <head>To all the well affected, but ill adviſed of the weaker Sex, who are either turned, or turning from the way of the Church of Chriſt in Old <hi>England,</hi> to the refined Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of ſeperation, Specially thoſe in the Town of Great <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you is this <hi>Glaſſe</hi> preſented, with a <hi>Requeſt,</hi> That you will vouchſafe to <hi>look</hi> into it, and that with an <hi>Eye</hi> not <hi>prejudiced</hi> againſt it. Poſſibly you may here ſee more of <hi>Satan,</hi> and <hi>your ſelves,</hi> his <hi>wiles,</hi> your <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> then before you were aware of. If any ſhall herein eſpy ſome <hi>ſpots</hi> and <hi>blemiſhes</hi> diſcovered, not becoming the <hi>face of profeſſion,</hi> let them not blame the <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents things as they are, but <hi>themſelves,</hi> or <hi>others,</hi> who have given the <hi>ground</hi> to theſe <hi>Reflections.</hi> For my own <hi>Intentions,</hi> in holding forth this <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> they are ſuch as I can approve unto God, <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did.</hi> As for <hi>aſperſing of Religion, diſparaging the weaker Sex, diſcouraging of any in their holy indeavours of going before others in the profeſſion and power of godlineſſe, ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſpirits of any that are truly godly, or opening the
<pb facs="tcp:113261:3"/>mouthes of any that are profanely wicked,</hi> my heart ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me not with the <hi>guilt</hi> of any of them. That which firſt put this <hi>ſubject</hi> into my hand, was chiefly a tender reſpect to the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>welfare</hi> of this <hi>place</hi> where God hath caſt me. Where I could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a deep <hi>reſentment</hi> take notice how many of the <hi>weaker Sex,</hi> being by degrees diſtaſted with the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Ordinances,</hi> came at length to be quite <hi>weaned</hi> from them: No more owning that <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> or thoſe <hi>means</hi> which to ſome of them had been heretofore the avowed and acknowledged <hi>power of God to their ſalvation.</hi> For your ſakes were theſe <hi>meditations</hi> firſt <hi>conceived;</hi> And for your ſakes are they now <hi>brought forth</hi> to a more publike view: That ſo what you would not vouchſafe to <hi>heare</hi> with the <hi>eare,</hi> you may yet have opportunity to ſee with the <hi>eye.</hi> May the eyes of any of you be hereby <hi>opened,</hi> ſo as you may ſee the <hi>error</hi> of theſe your <hi>wandrings,</hi> and be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to returne againe to the <hi>fold</hi> from which you have ſtrayed, I ſhould account it an acceptable ſervice both to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>You.</hi> However, I ſhall acknowledge it no ſmall recompence, that ſome others may be ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>following</hi> after you. In the <hi>experience,</hi> and <hi>hopes</hi> whereof, with my hearty prayers unto God for them and you, I ſit downe, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Yarmouth.</dateline>
               <signed>Yours in the ſervice of Chriſt, <hi>JOHN BRINSLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113261:3"/>
            <head>A LOOKING-GLASSE FOR GOOD VVOMEN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 TIM. 214.</bibl>
                  <p>And Adam was not deceived, but the woman being deceived was in the tranſgreſſion.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text is Scripture, and ſuch a portion of Scripture, as is but too proper for the times wherein we live: Other Apology, I ſhall need none for my taking it up, and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it in this place.</p>
            <p>To make way to the words; Look but a little back into the Chapter, and you ſhall meet with a parcell of <hi>Apoſtolicall Canons,</hi> partly concerning <hi>Men,</hi> partly <hi>Women.</hi> The former you have in the 8. ver.
<note place="margin">Coherence.</note> 
               <hi>I will therefore that men pray every where, &amp;c.</hi> The latter in the four verſes following: Wherein the Apoſtle orders the <hi>female Sex:</hi> Firſt touching their <hi>Apparell,</hi> ver. 9, 10. <hi>In like manner alſo, that the women adorne themſelves in modeſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, &amp;c.</hi> Then touching their demeanour in the <hi>publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and ſervice of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.12. Wherein (as <hi>Henimgius</hi> reſolves thoſe two verſes) we may take notice of a double <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction,</hi> and a double <hi>Prohibition.</hi> Two things <hi>commanded,</hi> and two things <hi>prohibited.</hi> The things injoyned, are, that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>learn:</hi> 1. <hi>Silently,</hi> then <hi>ſubmiſſively: Let the women learn in ſilence, with all ſubjection,</hi> ver. 11.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113261:4"/>The things prohibited are; Firſt, their <hi>Publick teaching;</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, their <hi>uſurping authority over their husbands;</hi> I <hi>ſuffer not a woman to teach, nor to uſurpe Authority over the man,</hi> ver. 12. And both theſe the Apoſtle preſſeth by a twofold Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: The former taken from mans <hi>precedency in his Creation,</hi> ver. 13. <hi>For Adam was firſt formed then Eve.</hi> The woman was made after the man, and for the man; And therefore, for her to take upon her the office of <hi>Teaching,</hi> or to <hi>uſurpe authority</hi> over the man; what were it but to invert the courſe and order of nature: The latter taken from the <hi>Womans priority in her defection:</hi> That you have in the words of the Text, <hi>And Adam was not deceived, but the woman being deceived was in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words for our better handling of them,
<note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> we may take notice firſt of the <hi>Negative,</hi> then of the <hi>Poſitive</hi> part of them. The former concerning the firſt <hi>Man,</hi> denying him to have been deceived: <hi>And Adam was not deceived.</hi> The latter concerning the firſt <hi>woman;</hi> affirming her, firſt, to have been <hi>deceived;</hi> then, to have been in the <hi>tranſgreſſion: But the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp;c.</hi> Three clauſes, yeelding us three diſtinct Propoſitions, or Concluſions. 1. <hi>Adam was not deceived.</hi> 2. <hi>The woman was deceived.</hi> 3. Being deceived, <hi>ſhe was in the tranſgreſsion.</hi> Touch upon each, and but touch upon them, by way of <hi>Explication, Illuſtration,</hi> that ſo I may make way to <hi>Application,</hi> which is the main thing which at preſent I aime at.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Adam was not deceived</hi>] No? How came he then to fall?
<note place="margin">1. How it is ſaid that Adam was not deceived.</note> How came he to adventure upon the eating of that <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit,</hi> the <hi>core</hi> whereof yet ſticketh in the <hi>throats</hi> and <hi>hearts</hi> of all his poſterity to this day?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diverſly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> To this is anſwered variouſly: Six or ſeven reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (ſuch as they are) I finde returned to it by the Ieſuit <hi>Eſtius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſtius,</hi> Com. ad loc.</note> I ſhall only ſingle out two or three of them, ſuch as I finde moſt approved of by Orthodox Expoſitours.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Adam was not deceived,</hi> that is (ſay ſome) not <hi>formally,</hi> not <hi>properly,
<note place="margin">1. He was not deceived pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally.</note> Propriè nemo decipitur, niſi â decipiente</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſtius</hi>) Properly and formally no man is ſaid to be <hi>deceived,</hi> but by a <hi>Deceiver;</hi> who muſt be ſuch a one as hath <hi>animum fallendi;</hi> a minde and purpoſe to deceive; ſo was the <hi>woman</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113261:4"/>deceived by the <hi>Serpent</hi> (or rather by <hi>Satan</hi> in the <hi>Serpent</hi>) intending to deceive her. But ſo was not <hi>Adam</hi> deceived. The woman in tendring the <hi>Apple</hi> unto him, ſhe had no purpoſe to deceive him. <hi>Hoc ſecit decepta, non decipiens</hi> (ſaith the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Author) This ſhe did being her ſelf deceived, not with an intention to deceive her husband: No,
<note place="margin">Merc. in Gen. 3.6.</note> that which herein ſhe did, was only out of a deſire to make him partaker of her ſuppoſed happineſſe. As for <hi>deluding, deceiving</hi> of him, it was far from her thoughts. And hereupon (ſay ſome) it is ſaid, that <hi>Adam was not deceived:</hi> But this ſeemeth a little too acute, and curious.</p>
            <p n="2">2. More plainly and ſimply, (in the ſecond place) <hi>Adam was not deceived,</hi> that is, not <hi>Primarily;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Not primarily</note> he was not the firſt that was deceived: So ſome expound it, by borrowing a word from the verſe foregoing, which they conceive ſhould here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain be repeated, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>but Adam was not firſt deceived,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Verſe 13.</note> 
               <hi>but the Woman, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Adam was not deceived,</hi> viz. not <hi>Immediatly</hi> by the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:</hi> So was the <hi>Woman</hi> deceived, giving eare to Satan,
<note place="margin">3. Not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly by the Serpent.</note> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in and by the Serpent, ſhe was deceived; but ſo was not <hi>Adam</hi> deceived: Deceived indeed he was; but it was by the means of the <hi>Woman,</hi> handing thoſe ſuggeſtions unto him, which ſhe had received from the Serpent: withall, ſoliciting, and inticing him; to whom he yielded, partly, <hi>Ex àmicabili quâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam benevolentiâ,</hi> out of a loving and indulgent affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, and ſo was overcome, even as <hi>Sampſon</hi> was by his <hi>Dalilah,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> by his <hi>Wives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two laſt Reſolutions, (being in effect one and the ſame) we may ſafely pitch upon. <hi>Adam was not deceived,</hi> viz. ſo as the Woman was deceived: not <hi>firſtly,</hi> not <hi>immediatly,</hi> ſo was the Woman deceived; and being ſo deceived, ſhe was the <hi>Inſtrument to deceive her Husband:</hi> So it followeth; But <hi>The Woman being deceived, ſhe was in the Tranſgreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Woman was deceived.</hi>] So ſhe was both <hi>properly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</note> and <hi>primarily,</hi> and <hi>immediatly. How</hi> deceived? By what <hi>Means?</hi> By what <hi>Agent?</hi> By what <hi>Inſtrument?</hi> By what <hi>Arguments</hi> and <hi>Suggeſtions?</hi> You may read them all in that third of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> which I ſhall have occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113261:5"/>upon anon: For the preſent I ſhall onely enquire;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Why Satan ſingles out the woman to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her?</note> Why <hi>Satan</hi> ſingles out the <hi>Woman?</hi> Why he firſt ſets upon her, to deceive and ſeduce her?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For this take a double reaſon: Satan looked upon her as a fitting <hi>Object,</hi> and a fitting <hi>Inſtrument:</hi> A fitting <hi>Object</hi> to work <hi>upon,</hi> and a fitting <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to work <hi>by.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A fitting Object to work upon:</hi> In as much as ſhe was the <hi>weaker Veſſell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. She was the more fit object to work upon, in regard of her weakneſſe.</note> leſſe able to withſtand the ſtroke of his Temptations. Had he encountred with the Man, there might have been more probability of reſiſtance, leſſe hope of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing: Therefore he ſingles out the Woman, as apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more hopes of prevailing there, by reaſon of the naturall infirmity of her Sex.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As fit to <hi>work upon,</hi> ſo to <hi>work by;</hi> A fitting <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> being her ſell deceived,
<note place="margin">2. A fit inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to work by, in decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the man.</note> to deceive her Husband, by convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame ſuggeſtions unto him, who would the leſſe ſuſpect what came through her hands, of whoſe cordiall and entire affection he was ſo ſully perſwaded. <hi>Such Inſtruments Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan often maketh uſe of in ſeducing of others: Vnſuſpected In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments:</hi> ſuch was the <hi>Woman</hi> to her <hi>Husband.</hi> And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Satan</hi> ſingles out her, that ſhe being her ſelf deceived might be the Inſtrument to deceive him, which accordingly came to paſſe; ſo it followeth in the Text.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The woman being deceived, ſhe was in the tranſgreſsion;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the tranſgreſsion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. How the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is ſaid to be in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</note> The phraſe here imports two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hereby ſhe became a <hi>Tranſgreſſour; Obnoxia facta eſt Tranſgreſsioni;</hi> So <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> ſhe became obnoxious, guilty of the tranſgreſſionof the Law of God;
<note place="margin">1. She was a tranſgreſſour.</note> a truth, but not the whole truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She being hereby made a <hi>Tranſgreſſour,</hi> ſhe became alſo the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Originall of tranſgreſsion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. And the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</note> ſo <hi>Beza, Cauſa tranſgreſsionis fuit; She was the cauſe of tranſgreſsion,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>put for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſo <hi>Ambroſe</hi> renders it well, <hi>Facta eſt in Praevaricationem.</hi> She became the <hi>means</hi> and <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to ſeduce her husband, and ſo to draw him into the like tranſgreſſion. A truth, which for the doctrinall part of it, is ſo clearly held forth by the Spirit of God in that third of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that it admits of no further, either <hi>Confirmation</hi> or <hi>Illuſtration.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113261:5"/>
            <p>That which I mainly aimed at when I took this <hi>Text</hi> in hand,
<note place="margin">Introduction to Application</note> was the making of it uſefull to the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> wherein we live: Wherein, let not any of your <hi>jealous thoughts</hi> anticipate, and forerun my <hi>innocent Meditations,</hi> as if I intended to caſt any <hi>Diſrespect</hi> upon the <hi>weaker Sex,</hi> which as God hath many wayes honoured, ſo ſhall I; much leſſe, any <hi>Diſparagement</hi> upon any of the <hi>wayes of God,</hi> wherein any of them deſire to walk; not yet to rebate the edge, or cool the fervour of a holy and well tempered <hi>Zeal</hi> in them or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Far be all theſe from my thoughts, and yours: My in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions herein are candid, and ſo I hope ſhall my words be, free from all gall and bitterneſſe, and (as much as may be) from ſharpneſſe; which yet (I muſt tell you) the <hi>Miniſter of Chriſt</hi> may in ſome caſes make uſe of, and that not without good warrant from the Apoſtle;
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.10.</note> who writing unto <hi>Titus</hi> concerning ſome perſons that were <hi>unruly,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly</hi> and <hi>Refractory,</hi> viz. to the <hi>Reprehenſions, Admonitions,</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> of the Church, (as the Reverend <hi>Diodate</hi> gloſſeth upon the word;) and <hi>Vain-talkers,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes tended more to the ingendring of ſtrife, then to Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and <hi>Deceivers,</hi> Seducers, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as deceived the mindes, and ſo ſeduced otherwiſe well-meaning ſoules;
<note place="margin">Verſe 13.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Rebuke ſharply,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Preciſè,</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe &amp; down right termes, not ſmoothing them up in their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; nor yet going about the Buſh to tell them of their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariages; This courſe I might take: But I ſhall for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (as much as may be) decline it,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.21.</note> chooſing rather to come unto you in the <hi>ſpirit of meekneſſe,</hi> remembring who they are whom I have chiefly now to deal with; <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>weaker</hi> and tenderer <hi>Sex,</hi> and ſome of thoſe of tender <hi>Conſciences,</hi> I ſhall deal with them accordingly;
<note place="margin">Gen. 33.13, 14.</note> Even as <hi>Jacob</hi> dealt with his <hi>Children,</hi> which were <hi>tender,</hi> and his <hi>Cattel which were great with yong,</hi> he will not over-drive them, for fear of miſcariage; but will lead them on ſoftly, ſo as they may be able to indure it. So ſhall my deſire be to deal with you, with as much mildneſſe and tenderneſſe as may be: And to that end, I ſhall baulk and decline <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> of <hi>Reprehenſion,</hi> which yet the <hi>Text</hi> gives a fitting occaſion for, and the <hi>inordinate practiſes</hi> of ſome amongſt us, have too juſtly merited, of whom I may ſay, and that but too
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113261:6"/>truly, That <hi>they have been, and are but too willing to be deceived;</hi> Betaking my ſelf onely to <hi>Inſtructions</hi> and <hi>Directions;</hi> which I ſhall direct firſt to the <hi>one Sex,</hi> then to the <hi>other;</hi> Beginning with that which the Text directly and properly leadeth me to, the <hi>weaker</hi> Sex, the <hi>Woman;</hi> Concerning whom it informs us; Firſt,
<note place="margin">Application to Women.</note> that ſhe was <hi>Deceived:</hi> And ſecondly, That being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ſhe <hi>was in the Tranſgreſſion.</hi> Each uſefull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> Was it the <hi>Woman</hi> that was ſo deceived at the firſt? Then, <hi>let thoſe of that Sex learn hence to be for ever jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of themſelves;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Let them be for ever jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, leaſt they be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> Being Conſcious of their own naturall <hi>infirmity</hi> and <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> withall of their naturall proneneſſe and propenſity to be deceived and miſled; let them be for ever jealous over themſelves, cautelous and wary, leaſt they alſo ſhould be deceived. That they are naturally more prone to be deceived and miſled;
<note place="margin">Women natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally more prone to be deceived.</note> had former ages never yielded any evidence for it, the preſent times would afford but too many inſtances of it; not to go out of thoſe walls within which our ſelves live. How many of <hi>Eves Daughters</hi> do we daily here ſee following their <hi>Mother?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praeſtigiatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ne ſinito vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere,</hi> Exod. 22.18.</note> being deceived, drawn aſide, to the imbracing of the Errors of the times; ſome one way, ſome another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Woman is deceived:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Preſtigiatrix potius nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quià procti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niores ſunt ad hoc ſietas ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitate muli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eres.</hi> Iun. ad. loc.</note> I wiſh I might ſpeak it in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Text, and ſay, that <hi>The Man were not.</hi> It cannot be denyed; ſome alſo of that <hi>Sex</hi> are gone along with them, being carried away with the ſtream: But (bleſſed be God,) the number of them is not conſiderable. As it was at the firſt, ſo now, (it cannot be hid) <hi>The Woman, the Woman,</hi> ſhe is deceived.</p>
            <p>Now ſurely, thus it would not be, were there not a naturall aptitude,
<note place="margin">Speciall Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them required.</note> and inclination in that Sex to be deceived. Taking notice hereof, be excited in the name and fear of the Lord, to be the more wary, the more circumſpect over your ſelves: which if you be not,
<note place="margin">The firſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the beſt of Woman.</note> he that deceived your great <hi>Grandmother,</hi> (a <hi>good Woman</hi>) as good, nay take it not amiſſe if I ſay, <hi>better</hi> then the beſt of you, (ſuch I am ſure ſhe was, when Satan firſt met with her,) will alſo deceive you. Hereof the Spirit of God giveth you warning, by ſetting before you this fatall miſcariage of your firſt Parent. <hi>The Woman,</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> Woman, ſhe was deceived: And wherefore is this Recorded? Why? even as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113261:6"/>the Apoſtle ſaith of the <hi>Murmurings</hi> and <hi>Luſtings</hi> of the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, and the conſequents of them;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.6.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe things were for our Examples, that we ſhould not luſt as they alſo luſted; we ſhould not murmur, as they alſo murmured.</hi> So may I ſay of <hi>Eves</hi> being deceived. This ſtands upon Record for your <hi>Example,</hi> for your <hi>Admonition,</hi> to the intent, that <hi>you ſhould not be deceived, as ſhe alſo was deceived.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. As ſhe was deceived?</hi> Why, How was that?
<note place="margin">How the firſt Woman came to be deceived.</note> The Reſolution of this Queſtion will prove very uſefull for our preſent deſigne and purpoſe. As the <hi>Mother</hi> was deceived, ſo are her <hi>Daughters:</hi> As the firſt Woman was deceived at the firſt, ſo are many of that Sex deceived at this very day. Loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon the one, you ſhall ſee the other. But how was the firſt Woman deceived?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſhew you how, will you go along with me, with your <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Attention:</hi> I ſhall lead you through the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Doors,</hi> at which this deceit brake in upon her: And as I go along, I ſhall ſtill <hi>ſhut</hi> and <hi>bar</hi> them after me, that the like deceit may not break in upon any of you at any of them.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Doors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The wayes &amp; means of her deceiving, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to three Heads.</note> theſe <hi>wayes</hi> and <hi>means</hi> (I mean) whereby the Woman came to be deceived, are many: I ſhall reduce them all to three Heads. They were either in the <hi>Woman</hi> her ſelf, or in the <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> or in the <hi>Object:</hi> In every of theſe we ſhall meet with ſome particulars ſuiting very fitly with our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe: All which you ſhall finde laid down in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of that one Chapter, the third of <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Look upon the <hi>Woman</hi> her ſelf, and ſee what there was in her that occaſioned this her deception.
<note place="margin">1. In the woman her ſelfe.</note> In her take notice of three or four particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Her diſlike of, and diſcontentedneſſe with her preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> God had made her after his own Image,
<note place="margin">1. Cauſleſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentedneſſe with her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition.</note> both Holy and Happy: So ſhe was, and ſo ſhe might have been, had ſhe but known her own happineſſe. But upon <hi>Satans tampering</hi> with her, ſhe took ſome diſlike that ſhe was not <hi>ſo</hi> well, ſo <hi>holy,</hi> ſo <hi>happy,</hi> as ſhe might have been, and as another was; ſhe was not as God. Again, God had placed her in <hi>Paradice,</hi> where ſhe had what ever her heart could deſire, the free uſe of all the choice Fruits of the Garden: Only there was one <hi>Tree,</hi> which ſhe might <hi>ſee,</hi> but not <hi>touch,</hi> at leaſt not <hi>taſte</hi> of; the <hi>Tree of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113261:7"/>Knowledge.</hi> And hereupon, being inſtigated by Satan, ſhe groweth <hi>diſcontented,</hi> and that diſcontent was the firſt ſtep to her fall and ruine: All which may be, and by Expoſitors ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally is collected from Satans <hi>Suggeſtions,</hi> and her <hi>Replies</hi> to them in the ſix firſt verſes of that Chapter.</p>
            <p>Now (beloved in the Lord) is it not the very ſelf ſame door that the <hi>Errors of the Times</hi> do ordinarily firſt break in at up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe which are deceived by them,
<note place="margin">Applied to the preſent ſtate of the times.</note> whether <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Errors of the times brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in at the ſame door.</note> They firſt fall into diſlike with their preſent ſtate and condition: Notwithſtanding, that they are <hi>well,</hi> yet they are not <hi>ſo</hi> well, ſo well as they would be, and as they apprehend ſome others to be: True indeed, they do injoy many precious <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Immunities:</hi> They do, or may partake in all the Holy Ordinances of God, <hi>Word, Sacraments, Prayer:</hi> Onely there is <hi>one Ordinance,</hi> which the Church at preſent hath not the exerciſe of, viz. <hi>Diſcipline, Government:</hi> And when it hath it, yet they conceive (this I ſpeak of <hi>Men,</hi> for <hi>Women</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet challenged it,) it ſhall not be <hi>put into their hands;</hi> they may no more <hi>touch</hi> it, then <hi>Vzzah</hi> might the <hi>Ark,</hi> or <hi>Eve</hi> the <hi>Apple.</hi> And hereupon they grow <hi>Diſcontented,</hi> and fall into diſlike with the preſent <hi>ſtate of the Church;</hi> and that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content layeth them open to Satans deluſions, who rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily worketh upon ſuch an advantage. And indeed, a greater advantage he cannot have.
<note place="margin">A diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpirit, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans Forge and Anvile.</note> 
               <hi>A diſcontented ſpirit is a forge and Anvile fit for Satan to forge and hammer any thing upon that is evil:</hi> In the fear of God would you not be deceived as your <hi>Mother</hi> was; take heed of ſuch a ſpirit: Beware how you entertain groundleſſe and cauſleſſe diſlikes, which ſhould make you diſcontented with your preſent <hi>perſonall ſtate,</hi> or the <hi>ſtate of the Church</hi> of God wherein you live.</p>
            <p>Miſtake it not: Not but that Chriſtians may take notice of both: As of their own <hi>perſonall wants,</hi> ſo of what is defective or wanting in the <hi>Church:</hi> And taking notice of it, they not onely may, but ought by all lawfull wayes and means to ſeek a ſupply: But through the apprehenſions of that defect, to grow diſcontented and impatient, ſo as thereupon to ſleight and undervalue all other the mercies which they injoy: This is a <hi>dangerous weakneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſuch a weakneſſe, as Gods own <hi>dear, deareſt ſervants</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113261:7"/>are ſubject to. It was <hi>Abrahams</hi> caſe you know, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.
<note place="margin">Gods own ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſubject to it.</note> When God cometh to him, with as ſweet and full a promiſe as could be brought to him, telling him that he <hi>was, and would be, his ſhield, and exceeding great reward:</hi> What ſaith <hi>Abraham?
<note place="margin">Gen. 15.1.2.</note> Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>What wilt thou give me, ſo long as I go childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe?</hi> Even ſo ſay ſome amongſt us at this day, when they hear what great things God hath already done for this Church of his, and what further mercies he ſeemeth to be about to reach forth unto it, in the liberty and purity of his Ordinances; yet what are all theſe to them? ſo long as there is ſome one thing, which for the preſent they want, and for the future have little hope to injoy.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Siſters</hi> (for to you I am now principally ſpeaking) take we heed all of us of ſuch dangerous,
<note place="margin">A Caveat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt cauſleſſe diſcontents.</note> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious <hi>diſcontents</hi> as theſe, the very <hi>Spawne,</hi> and <hi>firſt borne of Satan.</hi> So they were in the <hi>firſt woman;</hi> The firſt product and iſſue of Satans temptations in her, was a <hi>ſecret diſlike of, and diſcontentedneſſe with her preſent condition,</hi> the condition wherein God himſelf had ſet her; and that letteth in a <hi>Sea of Temptations</hi> upon her, ſo making way from her ſeduction.</p>
            <p>To prevent or heal the like evil in you,
<note place="margin">Our preſent diſcontents ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, and found to be ſuch.</note> give me leave in the <hi>ſpirit of meekneſſe</hi> a little to reaſon with you, about the ground of this diſcontent; I beſeech you, what is it that ſhould ſo far diſtaſte any of you with the preſent ſtate and condition of the Church of God in this Kingdom, and with the <hi>way,</hi> which you apprehend to be now laying forth unto you, as that you ſhould <hi>deſert</hi> the one, and <hi>decline</hi> the other? Certainly, if there be any ground at all for this diſlike, it muſt ariſe from one of theſe two <hi>heads;</hi> either from <hi>ſomething that you want and would have,</hi> or elſe from <hi>ſomething that you have, and would be freed from.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the latter: What <hi>burdens</hi> are there,
<note place="margin">Old burdens taken off.</note> which at the preſent lie upon this Church, which are ſo <hi>gravanimous,</hi> which the tendereſt conſcience, being rightly informed, may not ſubmit unto. As for thoſe <hi>ſtumbling blocks,</hi> the cauſe (or rather occaſion) of the unhappy <hi>Separation</hi> of the laſt age, (viz. <hi>Ceremonies and humane inventions, mingled with the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of God.</hi>) I think it will not be denied, but that they are removed, and taken out of the way: What then is the grievance?</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113261:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> But happily there is ſomething that you want &amp; would have.
<note place="margin">Pure Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces here admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred.</note> And what may that be? Why, <hi>Pure Ordinances.</hi> And have you not them? Is not the <hi>word</hi> truly preached unto you? Are not the <hi>Sacraments</hi> rightly-adminiſtred amongſt you?</p>
            <p>Poſsibly ſome may here hit that <hi>old blot,</hi> and challenge our <hi>mixtures in Church-Communion:</hi> That in participating in holy myſteries the <hi>Precious are not ſeparated from the Vile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15.19.</note> as they ought to be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And are they not? I beſeech you where lieth the fault? For <hi>us</hi> of the Miniſtry, what can we do mere then we have done? And for <hi>you,</hi> hath there not been a Liberty in this place publikely granted, for any who intended to come to the <hi>Table of the Lord,</hi> to give in any juſt exceptions (in time convenient) againſt any, who ſhould tender themſelves to that holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, being perſons juſtly <hi>obnoxious,</hi> either <hi>ignorant,</hi> or <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous?</hi> together with a promiſe of a <hi>ſtricter ſcrutiny and diſcrimination</hi> for the future, according to <hi>power committed</hi> (or rather <hi>tranſmitted</hi>) by <hi>lawfull Authority:</hi> And what can be more done for the preſent?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The exerciſe of Diſcipline to be warted for.</note> Why, but there wants the <hi>Exerciſe of diſcipline and Government</hi> for the right ordering of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To yield it: What then? will you not ſtay and expect till that Order can be drawn up? and the power for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thereof be duly and regularly tranſmitted?</p>
            <p>You know whoſe ſpeech it was,
<note place="margin">2 Kin. 6. ult.</note> and how ill it was taken, <hi>What ſhould I wait for the Lord any longer?</hi> Let there not be ſuch a Rebellious thought in any of our hearts. We have waited, and let us yet wait. Shall we precipitate the work and run before God? it may happen unto us, as it daily doth to many others: Even as to <hi>paſſengers in a ferry boat,</hi> that will be ſtepping and leaping out before the <hi>Boat</hi> can be haled to <hi>ſhore,</hi> where ſome are <hi>over ſhoes</hi> (as <hi>Separatiſts</hi>) others <hi>over head and ears</hi> (as <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and ſome others) ſo drenching or plunging our ſelves into dangerous and deſtructive errors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply,</hi> But wherefore ſhould we wait? When we have what is expected, yet will not that ſatisfie our deſires. There is yet ſome one thing more: And what is that? Why, the <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and abſolute government of every Church,</hi> every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation within it ſelf, commonly (how fitly, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113261:8"/>not) knowne by the name of <hi>Independency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Now herein God be mercifull to us,
<note place="margin">Affectation of Independency the undoing of the world at firſt.</note> and to his Churches: Was it not ſuch an other thing that <hi>undid the world at firſt: viz.</hi> The <hi>inordinate affectation of Independency:</hi> Our firſt parents would be <hi>abſolute:</hi> Me thinks the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance hereof, ſhould make us for ever jealous both of the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> But what if Chriſt have purchaſed and given ſuch a <hi>Liberty,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Priviledge</hi> to his Church? Ought not we to ſtand for the maintaining of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> What if? As for thoſe who make this plea,
<note place="margin">Independency of Churches no priviledge.</note> let them but ſhew their <hi>Charter,</hi> and we ſhall yield to it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time know we, that this is no ſuch priviledge, as it is by many taken to be: Nay, in truth no <hi>priviledge</hi> at all. For a Church to <hi>ſubſiſt</hi> alone, and to exerciſe ſuch an <hi>entire</hi> and <hi>abſolute juriſdiction</hi> within it ſelf, true, it may do it (<hi>viz.</hi> In caſe of <hi>neceſſity</hi>) but not ſo well: <hi>Adam</hi> when he was <hi>alone,</hi> he might have ſo ſubſiſted. But he who knew what was better for him concluded it,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>that it was not good for the man to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</hi> No more is it for <hi>Churches,</hi> which are likely to ſtand, and flouriſh, ſurer and better in a holy and brotherly <hi>Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and <hi>Go-ordinate ſubjection,</hi> then in a divided, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected <hi>ſingularity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſſe I am tranſported beyond my intentions: But you ſee how (as it is in <hi>errors</hi>) one thing draweth on another: I ſhall make you amends in ſome of the following particulars: You now ſee the firſt of them; paſſe we to the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place,
the <hi>woman</hi> being diſcontented with her preſent ſtate,
<note place="margin">2. The womans inordinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of better<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by any way propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> ſhe is <hi>inordinatly deſirous to better it by what ever way or means ſhould be propounded to her.</hi> I, be it to <hi>touch,</hi> and <hi>taste the Apple,</hi> though a <hi>prohibited fruit,</hi> yet ſo there may be but hopes of bettering her condition, ſhe will adventure upon it. And is it not ſo (beloved) with ſome amongſt us (as it is with many in ſome other parts of the Kingdom?) who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcontented with their preſent condition, they will adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon any way or means that ſhall be reached forth unto them by what hand ſo ever, with hopes of bettering it; It mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not though <hi>prohibited by the Laws of men,</hi> and for ought they know, may be ſo by the <hi>Laws of God,</hi> yet they will try it;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113261:9"/>ſo running from <hi>way</hi> to <hi>way</hi> (even as <hi>Solomon</hi> did from <hi>vanity</hi> to <hi>vanity</hi>) and from <hi>Church</hi> to <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seekers.</note> till they have run tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and out-run all the Churches in the world, and ſo have loſt both the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>themſelves,</hi> coming at length to ſtand alone (like a loſt ſheep in a deſert) as the new and ſtrange <hi>Generation of ſeekers</hi> at this day are ſaid to do.</p>
            <p>Beloved,
<note place="margin">A dangerous adventure to try every new way.</note> a <hi>dangerous adventure:</hi> For you (in the fear of God) take heed how you make it. Shall you ſo deal with your <hi>Bodies,</hi> take every <hi>medicine</hi> that is preſcribed you, it matters not by what adventrous, and unskilfull <hi>Emperick,</hi> you may make but ill work in the end: Surely your <hi>ſouls</hi> challenge as much, and more care from you: Take heed how you embrace every new way which is held forth unto you, how promiſing ſoever. In this caſe <hi>look</hi> before you <hi>leap;</hi> and <hi>Try before you Try:</hi> Be thorowly convinced, and ſee good and clear evidence out of the word, before you renounce, and engage your ſelves againſt any received <hi>truth;</hi> or yet againſt that <hi>way</hi> which the Church of God in this Kingdom is now holding forth unto you, betaking your ſelves to <hi>nevv vvaies</hi> different from it, much more contrary to it. Otherwiſe you may be <hi>deceived;</hi> Nay, let me tell you, this is the next way to be ſo, to pitch upon new wayes without due <hi>examination,</hi> and <hi>Tryall:</hi> So was the <hi>vvoman</hi> deceived at the firſt; being diſcontented with her firſt condition, ſhe adventureth upon a <hi>nevv way</hi> for the bettering of it, though held forth by <hi>Satan</hi> himſelf to her <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A third thing in the woman, which made way for her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving,
<note place="margin">3. The womans curioſity in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of a prohibited no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty. Gen. 3.3.</note> was her <hi>Curioſity,</hi> her <hi>affecting of Novelties,</hi> and that ſo much the rather, becauſe <hi>prohibited;</hi> Such was the <hi>Tree of knowledge:</hi> The <hi>Fruit</hi> thereof ſhe had not yet <hi>taſted:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides there lay a <hi>prohibition</hi> upon it: She might not touch it; So ſhe tels the <hi>Serpent,</hi> (though therein ſhe ſeemed to adde ſomewhat to the <hi>prohibition</hi>) And no queſtion this was one thing that edged her teeth, and made her fingers itch at it: It was a <hi>prohibited Novelty.</hi> And is there not a tang of this <hi>curioſity</hi> to be found generally in all the <hi>ſons</hi> and <hi>daughters</hi> of this <hi>common Mother?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Female Sex much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with novelties.</note> Specially in the latter. The <hi>Female Sex,</hi> how exceedingly are many of them affected with <hi>novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? New faſhions</hi> in apparell, though never ſo uncouth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113261:9"/>and uncomely, yet if <hi>New,</hi> how are they taken up by them?
<note place="margin">The Female Sex much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with Novelties.</note> Thus it ſhould not be amongſt <hi>Chriſtian women. Paul</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them another Leſſon in the ninth verſe of this Chapter, <hi>I will that women adorne themſelves in modeſt Apparell,
<note place="margin">New faſhions.</note> with ſhamefaſtneſſe and ſobriety, not with broyded</hi> (or <hi>playted) hair, or gold, or pearls, or coſtly aray;</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.9.</note> not affecting new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, gariſh dreſſes, or rich apparell, unſuitable to their qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and degree. But thus it is amongſt too many: And is it not ſo (I beſeech you be not unwilling to hear of it) with new <hi>Opinions,</hi> new <hi>Wayes,</hi> new <hi>Doctrines,</hi> new <hi>Truths,</hi> new <hi>Light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">New opinions and wayes, &amp;c.</note> new <hi>Teachers,</hi> new <hi>Phraſes</hi> and <hi>Expreſſions?</hi> O how do theſe affect? and that oft times for no other Reaſon, but for the <hi>Novelty</hi> of them, becauſe they are <hi>New:</hi> Specially if <hi>Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited,</hi> that ſets a further gloſſe upon them, making <hi>Women,</hi> (I, and <hi>Men</hi> too oft times) the more earneſt in looking after them: <hi>The men of Bethſhemeſh</hi> will be looking into the <hi>Ark,</hi> though it coſt them their lives for it, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 6.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Such is the <hi>corrupt nature</hi> of Man,
<note place="margin">Corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture delights to ſwim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtream.</note> that (like as it is with ſome Fiſhes) it delighteth to <hi>ſwim againſt the ſtream. Niti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur in vetitum.</hi> Things are the more deſired becauſe forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Even as it is with <hi>ſick perſons;</hi> what the <hi>Phiſician prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites,</hi> that they moſt <hi>long</hi> for. Thus what <hi>Authority</hi> forbids, that the <hi>ſick nature</hi> of man oft times moſt <hi>affects;</hi> a truth which I might make good in many particular inſtances; But I ſpare you.</p>
            <p>Thus it is, (and I think, if you will but every one feel your own pulſe, you will acknowledge it ſo to be,)
<note place="margin">Novelty in Religion, no commendation but a diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.</note> but thus it ſhould not be. In <hi>Religion, Novelty</hi> is no <hi>Commendation,</hi> but a <hi>Diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.</hi> Even as it is with <hi>Wines;</hi> The <hi>New</hi> may be <hi>ſweeter,</hi> pleaſanter, but the <hi>Old</hi> is <hi>wholeſomer,</hi> I, and (to a judicious Palate) <hi>toothſomer</hi> too. <hi>No man having drunk Old Wine,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour,)
<note place="margin">Luke 5. ult.</note> (<hi>viz.</hi> being able to judge of Wine) <hi>ſtreightway deſireth New;</hi> for he <hi>ſaith the Old is better.</hi> Even ſo is it in <hi>Religion. New wayes</hi> may be ſweet, and pleaſant to thoſe that firſt enter into them. I, but the <hi>Old</hi> is <hi>better, ſafer, ſurer.</hi> And therefore it is that the Lord by the Prophet biddeth the people enquire for the <hi>Old</hi> way. <hi>Ask for the Old way,
<note place="margin">Ier. 6.16.</note> which is the good way, and walke therein.</hi> The <hi>Old way,</hi> that way which the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> walked in. And ſo the <hi>Old way,</hi> that way
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113261:10"/>which the <hi>Apoſtles and Apoſtolicall Churches,</hi> being directed by the Spirit of God, walked in. This is the <hi>Old way,</hi> and this is the <hi>good way.</hi> Enquire we for this.</p>
            <p>And is not this the <hi>way</hi> which the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is now ſeeking.
<note place="margin">The old way now ſought for in and by the Kingdom.</note> To which end, the beſt courſe that can be thought of, hath been taken. It was the courſe which King <hi>Herod</hi> took, (and it was the wiſeſt courſe that he could take,) when he would be rightly informed concerning <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf,
<note place="margin">The beſt means uſed to finde it out. Matth. 2.4, 5.</note> touching the place of his <hi>Nativity,</hi> he <hi>gathereth the chief Prieſts, and Scribes of the people together,</hi> conſulting with them about it. Like courſe hath <hi>Authority</hi> in this Kingdom, taken to finde out the <hi>Way of Chriſt.</hi> They have to this purpoſe gathered together ſome, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (let it be ſpoken without <hi>Flattery,</hi> and <hi>heard</hi> without <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi>) of the <hi>Chiefe Prieſts and Scribes of the people; Scribes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed unto the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> ſuch as in probability ſhould be beſt acquainted with the <hi>Myſteries of that Kingdom;</hi> Men of known <hi>Piety, Integrity, Ability;</hi> And with them they have now for a long time conſulted. And what more likely courſe can be taken for the finding out of that way? Now far be it from us,
<note place="margin">Take heed of cauſleſſe preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices againſt the way of the Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be known.</note> for any of us to entertain any <hi>cauſleſſe Prejudice,</hi> againſt that way before we know it; much more by any <hi>inconſiderate preingagements,</hi> by putting our ſelves into <hi>New wayes</hi> aforehand, to render our ſelves <hi>incapable</hi> of it, when God ſhall hold it forth unto us, though with never ſuch clear evidence of truth. Nay rather, as for theſe <hi>New wayes,</hi> how ſweet, and pleaſant, and plauſible ſoever they may ſeem to be; yet it will be a great deal more wiſdom to deal with them as <hi>Vintners</hi> do with their <hi>Wines,</hi> which they let <hi>stand</hi> and <hi>ſettle,</hi> before they <hi>pierce</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Let not <hi>Affectation</hi> of <hi>Novelty,</hi> of <hi>New wayes,</hi> inordinatly tranſport any of us, leaſt thereby unawares we be brought to reject and renounce <hi>old Truth,</hi> as ſome of late times have done.</p>
            <p>Much leſſe ſuffer we our ſelves to be carried on with a <hi>ſpirit of oppoſition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beware of a Spirit of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</note> to ſwim againſt the ſtream of <hi>Authority,</hi> ſo as to like any <hi>way</hi> the <hi>worſe,</hi> becauſe <hi>Commended</hi> and <hi>Commanded;</hi> or yet the <hi>better,</hi> becauſe <hi>prohibited</hi> and <hi>oppugned.</hi> True indeed, it is poſſible the way of God may be <hi>every where ſpoken againſt,</hi> (as the <hi>Jews</hi> tell <hi>Paul</hi> concerning his <hi>Sect.</hi>)
<note place="margin">Acts 28.22.</note> But it is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>way of God,</hi> becauſe ſpoken againſt. Much leſſe is it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113261:10"/>ever the <hi>better</hi> to be liked, becauſe every <hi>where</hi> ſpoken againſt True indeed, were it ſo that it were ſpoken againſt onely by <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> men, or by <hi>Time-ſerving ſuperſtitious For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malists;</hi> this might be like a <hi>dark ſhadow</hi> to a <hi>beautifull Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,</hi> that maketh it the more <hi>Lightſome;</hi> or a dark <hi>foyle,</hi> to a fair <hi>Diamond,</hi> which maketh it <hi>ſparkle</hi> the more. But when a way ſhall be oppugned by <hi>good</hi> men, <hi>holy</hi> men, <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>judicious</hi> men, and that not by a few <hi>private ſpirits,</hi> but by the <hi>generall conſent of the Churches,</hi> in this caſe certainly ſuch <hi>oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> renders it at leaſt very ſuſpicious. Let not any of us then like a way the <hi>better</hi> for this. Much leſſe becauſe <hi>Lawfull and Chriſtian Authority</hi> ſtrikes in againſt it. In this caſe Chriſtians ſhould be very wary, and tender,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1, 2.</note> leaſt in oppoſing and reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Powers which are of God,</hi> they alſo reſiſt God in them. I have done with the third Particular. Take but one more.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And that was, the Womans <hi>Incogitancy,</hi>
or <hi>unadviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Parleying with the Serpent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. The womans unadviſedneſſe in parlying with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of her husband, and conſenting to him without his privity.</note> entring <hi>diſpute or conference</hi> with him about a <hi>received Truth,</hi> and that not onely <hi>hearing</hi> of him, <hi>but hearkning</hi> unto him; nay, <hi>yielding,</hi> and <hi>conſenting,</hi> and <hi>ingaging</hi> her ſelf by an <hi>Act</hi> of her own, and all this without the <hi>privity of her husband,</hi> whom God had ſet over her, and who might have been able to have <hi>Reſolved</hi> and <hi>Informed</hi> her bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This (ſaith <hi>Pareus</hi>) this <hi>unadviſedneſſe</hi> or <hi>Raſhneſſe,</hi> (call it as we will) was the <hi>beginning and firſt occaſion of her down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall.</hi> And ſurely ſo it hath been in many of her <hi>Daughters,</hi> who have been deceived and ſeduced by the very ſame means,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parum conſultò ſe certanimi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculoſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit marito abſente vel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſulto. Iſta ſive incogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantia, ſive te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritas princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium fuit &amp; occaſio ſequentis lapſus.</hi> Pareus, in Gen. 3. ver. 2.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> through their own <hi>Adventrous Raſhneſſe</hi> in hearkning to ſubtile <hi>Deceivers,</hi> and <hi>Dangerous Seducers,</hi> (theſe tearms, when ever I uſe them, let it not be conceived that I have the leaſt thought of reflecting upon any of our Reverend and Godly Brethren of the <hi>Congregationall way,</hi> whoſe perſons I reſpect and honour, but in reference to ſome others, who by their ſmooth and ſubtile inſinuations, have drawn ſome of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker Sex into dangerous and deſtructive Errors,) and not only <hi>hearkning,</hi> but <hi>yielding, conſenting, ingaging</hi> themſelves in their wayes, and that without the <hi>conſent</hi> or <hi>privity</hi> of their <hi>Husbands,</hi> or without <hi>adviſing</hi> with <hi>any other</hi> who might have been more able to inform them.</p>
            <p>This <hi>latter clauſe</hi> I cannot but take notice of, and let you
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113261:11"/>know that I do ſo.
<note place="margin">The unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantableneſſe of womens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging them ſelves in new waies without the privity or conſent of their husbands</note> Not but that I might alſo take juſt occaſion to deal with the <hi>former,</hi> viz. <hi>the unwarrantable raſhneſſe and preſumption of ſome women in imbracing, and ingaging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in new vvaies without the privity of their husbands</hi> (and ſo of <hi>children</hi> without the conſent of <hi>Parents</hi>) to whom they are ſo far in duty bound, as to take their <hi>advice,</hi> (ſpecially if they be able to give it) however to acquaint them with their <hi>intentions,</hi> and the <hi>reaſons of them,</hi> deſiring their <hi>conſents:</hi> But letting that paſſe now,
<note place="margin">Peoples inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in new waies without conferring with their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> which probably I may have occaſion to touch upon again hereafter.</p>
            <p>The latter I cannot but take notice of, as being a matter which ſomewhat concerneth <hi>my ſelf,</hi> and my <hi>fellow-labourer</hi> in the Miniſtery here; whom God in reſpect of our <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Office,</hi> hath appointed to be as <hi>Counſellors</hi> to his people in things appertaining to himſelf: So runs that old <hi>Statute: They ſhould ſeek the Law at the Prieſts mouth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> Such is our <hi>Office,</hi> and ſuch <hi>uſe our people ought to make of it.</hi> But how few are there that do it? Herein let me appeal to the conſciences of thoſe that are gone aſide into any of the <hi>Errors of the times,</hi> how ſew are there of them that ever addreſſed themſelves to either of us to be reſolved in their doubts, and ſcruples of this kinde. Some I will not deny but have done it, who through the bleſſing of God have been at leaſt <hi>ſtayed,</hi> if not <hi>ſatisfied.</hi> But how few?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply,</hi> I know what will here preſently be replied; Though <hi>we</hi> have not heard of them, yet ſome others have: ſuch as they apprehended able enough to reſolve them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But who were thoſe <hi>others?</hi> were they not ſuch as they were perſwaded would <hi>ſpeak</hi> what they were deſirous to <hi>hear?</hi>
               <note place="margin">A pretended, but falſe way of ſeeking re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</note> Such whoſe <hi>judgements</hi> they knew beforehand to be conſonant, and agreeable to their own <hi>mindes</hi> and <hi>wills:</hi> If ſo, then <hi>this is not the way to be reſolved, but rather to be confirmed in a Reſolution.</hi> You know it was <hi>Ahabs</hi> caſe, (let none abuſe the <hi>Compariſon,</hi> by ſtretching it beyond the Staple, extending it beyond the point to which it is intended. Sure I am, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours parables of the <hi>Theef,</hi> and <hi>unjuſt Steward</hi> will bear it out) <hi>Ahab</hi> pretending to <hi>ſeek reſolution</hi> concerning his <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition againſt Ramoth-Gilead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings, cap. ult.</note> whether he ſhould go up to it, or no, he conſults with the <hi>Prophets</hi> about it. But what Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113261:11"/>His <hi>own</hi> Prophets, ſuch as he preſumed would ſpeak what he would have. But as for that other <hi>Prophet of God</hi> whom <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> mindes him of, in as much as he ſuſpected him to be of another minde, and ſo would be averſe to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended deſigne, therefore he declines him, is loath to confer or conſult with him. Now this I ſay, is not to <hi>ſeek,</hi> but rather to <hi>confirme Reſolution.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable way to be reſolved in ſcruples.</note> The way to be reſolved in <hi>ſcruples</hi> and <hi>doubts</hi> of this nature, is to hear what <hi>both parties</hi> can lay, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe of a <hi>differing judgement</hi> from our ſelves. This is the moſt probable, and rationall way to be rightly informed.</p>
            <p>And is it ſo? The more is the wonder that it ſhould be ſo much neglected, and declined as it is, and that not onely in private, but (as the report is) alſo in <hi>publick.</hi> Strange, are there any ſuch? (I ſhould hope there are not) who are ſo far <hi>wedded</hi> to their own <hi>wills,</hi> as to take up <hi>reſolutions</hi> aforehand, in caſe their <hi>opinions</hi> be medled with,
<note place="margin">An evadence of ſome that are too willing be deceived.</note> or their <hi>wayes</hi> touched upon, though never ſo <hi>tenderly,</hi> yet they will come no more at the <hi>publick Ordinance,</hi> at leaſt not to hear ſuch a Miniſter? Now ſurely <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Is this <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> Even <hi>Foelix</hi> the <hi>Heathen</hi> was of a better minde, or at leaſt durſt not avouch ſuch high, and preſumptuous obſtinacy: At the hearing of <hi>Pauls Sermon,</hi> he was troubled, and much troubled, yet he promiſeth to hear him again another time. Shall any dare to reſolve otherwayes? Let them take this home with them:
<note place="margin">Act. 24 25.</note> 
               <hi>This is but too clear an evidence, that they are but too willing to be deceived.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the firſt head of particulars, taken from the <hi>woman</hi> her ſelf, who gave occaſion to her own deceiving, by her <hi>Diſcontentedneſſe with her preſent condition;</hi> her <hi>inordinate deſire of bettering it by what ever way ſhould be propounded; her Curioſity in affecting of prohibited Novelties;</hi> and her <hi>unadviſed raſhneſſe in parlying with the adverſarie about a received truth, and not conſulting with her husband about it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſe we now to the ſecond head, looking upon the <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> which <hi>Satan</hi> made uſe of in deceiving the <hi>woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 The Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by which the woman was deceived.</note> the <hi>firſt</hi> woman, the <hi>beſt</hi> of women. And here again we ſhall meet with diverſe particulars, all very fitly appliable to our preſent purpoſe: Refer we them to two heads. The <hi>Quality of the Perſon,</hi> and his <hi>Arguments.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113261:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Quality of the Perſon.</hi> In the generall, an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſpected Inſtrument.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. The quality of the perſon; an unſuſpected Inſtrument.</note> Such <hi>Inſtruments</hi> doth <hi>Satan</hi> at this day make uſe of, in perverting and ſeducing of ſimple and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning ſouls; <hi>unſuſpected Inſtruments;</hi> ſuch as are neither ſuſpected by <hi>themſelves,</hi> nor <hi>others,</hi> to do any ſuch office.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not by <hi>Themſelves.</hi> Certainly the <hi>Serpent</hi> in deceiving the <hi>woman</hi> had no purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Such Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments now made uſe of by Satan.</note> no <hi>intention</hi> to do what it did. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Satan</hi> made uſe of it as his <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> ſpeaking in it, and by it. And ſurely ſo is it with many of thoſe who are made inſtrumentall in <hi>ſeducing</hi> and drawing others into errors at this day.
What herein they do, it is <hi>Praeter intentionem,</hi> they have no ſuch thought,
<note place="margin">1. Vnſuſpected by themſelves.</note> no ſuch purpoſe. Only they are ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acted, and carried on by <hi>Satan,</hi> who worketh in them and by them, being <hi>unſuſpected by themſelves.</hi> It was the caſe of that <hi>Old Prophet,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 13.15. (as is moſt probably conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) in deceiving, ſeducing of the <hi>Man of God,</hi> that <hi>cryed out againſt the Altar at Bethel;</hi> In turning him out of his way, he had no ill deſigne upon him, no evil intent towards him. What he therein did, he did only to expreſſe his affection to him, by giving him the beſt entertainment he could: Yet we ſee what was the iſſue. However, ſure we are, it was <hi>Peters</hi> caſe, when he ſuggeſted that <hi>Counſell</hi> to his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> that he ſhould not go up to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but rather decline that <hi>ſervice,</hi> thoſe <hi>ſufferings,</hi> which he had told his Diſciples awaited for him there.
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.22.</note> 
               <hi>Be it far from thee Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>This ſhall not be unto thee. (Councell</hi> as pernicious, as any that the <hi>Serpent</hi> gave to the <hi>Woman</hi> (had it been followed) the <hi>ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankinde</hi> depending upon the one, as the <hi>deſtruction</hi> thereof did upon the other:) Full little did <hi>Peter</hi> think what <hi>diſſervice</hi> herein he did; That he ſhould have any hand in croſſing the <hi>determinate Counſell</hi> of God, or in hindring that <hi>great good work,</hi> which his Lord and Maſter was then about, the <hi>Redemption of mankinde.</hi> No, what herein he did, he did it out of a true <hi>cordiall affection</hi> to his Lord and Maſter. Yet was he herein <hi>ſecretly</hi> inſtigated, and acted by <hi>Satan,</hi> abuſing and perverting his good intentions, to ſiniſter, dangerous, and deſtructive ends. So much is intimated by our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf in that tart Reprehenſion of his,
<note place="margin">Ver. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Get thee behinde me Satan, &amp;c.</hi> Certainly ſo fareth it with ſome, with many at this day; who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113261:12"/>are ſo active in drawing people aſide into the <hi>errors</hi> of the Times. This they do, not out of any ill will they have either to <hi>Chriſt</hi> or them; but rather out of a <hi>zealous affection</hi> which they bear to both. Only they are herein ſeeretly acted by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> who maketh uſe of that their <hi>prepoſterous zeal</hi> to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of his own deſignes, in <hi>diſturbing the peace of the Church</hi> for the preſent, and (if it might be) in hindering that <hi>great good work</hi> in hand, the <hi>Reformation</hi> of it for the future. Thus <hi>Satan</hi> maketh uſe of Inſtruments not ſuſpected by <hi>themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Much leſſe by <hi>others:</hi>
Full little (without Queſtion) did <hi>Eve</hi> think,
<note place="margin">2. Vnſuſpected by others.</note> that ſuch deadly <hi>poyſon</hi> ſhould be breathed out of the <hi>mouth</hi> of that <hi>ſmooth Creature,</hi> as ſhould impoyſon her, and all her Poſterity. And as little do many well-meaning ſouls at this day ſuſpect, that they ſhould ſuck <hi>errors</hi> from thoſe <hi>lips,</hi> which they apprehend to be like the <hi>Spouſes lips, Cant.</hi> 4.
<note place="margin">Cant. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (and in ſome reſpect they are ſo) <hi>Dropping as the Honycombe,</hi> having <hi>Hony and milk under their tongues;</hi> ſuch <hi>tongues</hi> as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them many <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>ſoul-refreſhing inſtructions,</hi> and <hi>conſolations.</hi> And yet even through ſuch <hi>lips</hi> doth Satan ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times breath forth both dangerous and deadly poyſon.</p>
            <p>A truth which may be verified in ſome of the <hi>Antinomian</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſticall Teachers</hi> and <hi>Preachers</hi> of the times. In whoſe <hi>Sermons</hi> and <hi>writings</hi> there may be found ſome very uſefull, profitable, comfortable <hi>Truths;</hi> and thoſe happily ſet out with ſweet, and ſoul-Raviſhing expreſſions. But withall, there is a mixture of <hi>poyſon</hi> with that <hi>hony:</hi> dangerous, and deſtructive <hi>errors,</hi> being <hi>interwoven</hi> with thoſe <hi>Truths.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven, and that as <hi>Thread</hi> is ſometimes with <hi>ſilke,</hi> where the <hi>warpe</hi> frets, and eats out the <hi>woofe:</hi> Or like ſome of thoſe <hi>leaprous garments</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Leviticus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 13.48.</note> where the <hi>Warpe</hi> might be <hi>clean,</hi> and yet the <hi>woofe</hi> infected with the <hi>Plague of Leproſie.</hi> Such <hi>Inſtruments</hi> doth Satan make uſe of in venting, and propagating of the errors of the times (in this not unlike the <hi>Serpent</hi> at firſt) <hi>unſuspected Inſtruments.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Serpent then an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, but ſubtle Creature, both applyed to ſome ſeducers.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I might deſcend here into ſome particulars, taking notice of ſome <hi>qualities</hi> in the <hi>Serpent</hi> at that time, which may very fitly be applied to ſome of thoſe <hi>ſeducers</hi> which are abroad in the world: as <hi>viz.</hi> his <hi>Innocency,</hi> and <hi>ſubtilty.</hi> The Serpent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113261:13"/>was then an <hi>Innocent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.1. 2 Cor. 11.3.</note> and harmleſſe Creature, as all the reſt of the Creatures then were before the fall; though full of <hi>poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> within, yet outwardly <hi>harmleſſe:</hi> But Secondly, a <hi>ſubtile</hi> creature <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>The Serpent was more ſubtile then any beaſt of the field.</hi> And truly if we look at ſome <hi>deceivers</hi> (inſtance in that <hi>Serpentine brood</hi> of <hi>Romiſh Ieſuites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Romiſh Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, and ſome Engliſh Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note> and I ſhall take leave to joyn ſome <hi>Engliſh Anabaptiſts</hi> with them) ſhall we not finde them ſuch, and that both for <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>ſubtilty?</hi> For <hi>Innocency;</hi> in their lives <hi>demure, auſtere, harmleſſe, blameleſſe</hi> not to be cenſured, not to be taxed. But withall <hi>ſubtile;</hi> I, more ſubtile then any ordinary generation of men; <hi>hiding their poyſon;</hi> withall, ſlily <hi>inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating</hi> and winding themſelves into the boſoms of others by their ſmooth and plauſible inſinuations: Cloſely conveying themſelves, and cunningly <hi>creeping in and out</hi> by their ſubtile <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions</hi> and <hi>diſtinctions,</hi> even as the <hi>Serpent</hi> could in and out of the Garden.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Deceivers</hi> (my <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Siſters</hi>) there are abroad in the world; even ſuch as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. Who by their <hi>ſleight of hand</hi> (their <hi>Cogging</hi> and <hi>Cheating,</hi> ſo the word there properly ſignifieth (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) a Metaphor taken from <hi>playing at Dice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> where <hi>Cheaters</hi> can <hi>Cog</hi> the Dice to make them ſerve their own turnes) and <hi>cunning craftineſſe, lie in wait to deceive.</hi> I will not charge this place with any of this kinde.
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.6.</note> Yet poſsibly there may be ſome ſuch, who (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle deſcribeth them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.) <hi>Creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women.</hi> And truly, it is to be feared ſome ſuch there have been even in this place, who though themſelves be gone, yet they have left ſome of their <hi>ſtings</hi> behinde them.</p>
            <p>Now the caſe ſtanding thus,
<note place="margin">Great need of caution.</note> that <hi>Satan</hi> maketh uſe of ſuch Inſtruments (ſuch as the Serpent at firſt was) in the generall, <hi>unſuſpected</hi> Inſtruments; In particular, <hi>Innocent,</hi> and <hi>ſubtile</hi> Inſtruments; O what need have you to be cautelous and wary? Not <hi>beleeving every ſpirit:</hi> That is Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> advice, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. <hi>Every ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.11.</note> that is, every one that pretends to, and boaſts of the <hi>ſpirit:</hi> Nay, in this ſenſe, believe not <hi>any ſpirit.</hi> What ſaith the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Let God be true, and every man a lyar.</hi> God only is <hi>Infallible.</hi> As for men, be they what they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113261:13"/>will, they are <hi>Lyars,</hi> and that both <hi>Paſſively,</hi> and <hi>Actively,</hi> ſubject to be deceived themſelves, and to deceive others. You ſee it in our <hi>common Mother,</hi> who hath transferred this her <hi>naturall infirmity</hi> to all her <hi>Poſterity.</hi> And therefore <hi>Try</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we <hi>Truſt. Try the ſpirits whether they be of God.</hi> Not <hi>reſigning</hi> up our <hi>belief</hi> to the <hi>judgement</hi> of what ever <hi>man</hi> or <hi>men.</hi> Though never ſo <hi>learned,</hi> never ſo <hi>holy,</hi> never ſo <hi>wiſe,</hi> never ſo <hi>innocent,</hi> yet take heed of giving the <hi>divine honour of an abſolute credence</hi> unto them, which is no leſſe then a a kinde of <hi>Anthropolatreia,</hi> a piece of <hi>Man-worſhip.</hi> But <hi>try their spirits;</hi> and try their <hi>Doctrines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſpeak in the firſt place with reference to my ſelf.
<note place="margin">The Spirits and Doctrines of all men to be tried.</note> What ever ſhall fall from my mouth, take it not up, unleſſe you ſee <hi>evidence</hi> for it, either in the <hi>vvord,</hi> or in the <hi>nature</hi> of the thing. And I wiſh you would do the like by all others. As for <hi>hearing</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> (ſuch I mean as are, (or at leaſt have been) <hi>Miniſters;</hi> for as for <hi>meer private perſons, Teaching Brethren</hi> (as they are called) I dare give no allowance to the <hi>publick exerciſe of their gift</hi> (as they call it) for which I know no warrant that they have either from <hi>God</hi> or <hi>man</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be in <hi>caſe</hi> of <hi>neceſſity,</hi> which (bleſſed be God) is not our caſe) but for the hearing of others, though in ſome things of <hi>different judgements,</hi> yet (ſo it may be done without any <hi>affront to Authoritie,</hi> and without giving any <hi>countenance to any of the errors</hi> of the times, and particularly to that of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi>) I diſ-allow it not. Only therein, take heed of <hi>ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in, and <hi>ſvvallovving dovvn</hi> all ſuch <hi>doctrines</hi> as ſhall be delivered by them, and that without any chewing, taking them upon the credit of the <hi>ſpeaker,</hi> leaſt in ſo doing, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome <hi>truthes,</hi> you alſo ſwallow downe ſome <hi>errors.</hi> So was your <hi>first mother</hi> deceived, <hi>viz.</hi> by giving <hi>ear</hi> to an <hi>unſuſpected Inſtrument,</hi> and taking the word from his <hi>mouth</hi> without <hi>due Tryall,</hi> ſhe took in that which might have proved the <hi>ruine</hi> of her, and all her poſterity. This for the <hi>Quality of the perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we now to his <hi>Arguments.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which Satan put into the Serpents mouth.</note> What were the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which <hi>Satan</hi> putteth into the <hi>Serpents</hi> mouth for the <hi>deceiving</hi> of our firſt parent? What were thoſe <hi>Reaſonings,</hi> thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Paul</hi> calleth them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.) thoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113261:14"/>
               <hi>Devices,</hi> thoſe <hi>Wiles</hi> or <hi>Methods</hi> (that is the Apoſtles word, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which this <hi>grand Deceiver</hi> here maketh uſe of? Of theſe take we notice of four or five.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is a <hi>doubtfull interrogation,</hi> wherein he <hi>questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth a received and known Truth.
<note place="margin">1. A doubtfull Interrogation, calling a known Truth into queſtion.</note> Yea, hath God indeed ſaid, ye ſhall not eat of every Tree of the Garden? Gen.</hi> 3.1. This <hi>Prohibition Eve</hi> had either <hi>heard from Gods ovvn mouth</hi> (as is moſt probable) or elſe ſhe had <hi>received it from her husband,</hi> and that with ſuch ſtrong and clear evidence, as that ſhe was fully convinced of it, as appeareth from the ſecond, and third verſes of that Chapter: Now <hi>Satan</hi> having to deal with her, the firſt thing that he attempts, is to kindle a <hi>jealouſie</hi> in her breaſt concerning that word; to render it ſuſpitious to her, as if either it were not true, or at leaſt not <hi>equall.</hi> And is not this the way whereby <hi>Satan</hi> ordinarily prepareth the hearts of thoſe whom he intendeth to deceive, for the receiving of his ſuggeſtions and deluſions? Firſt, he <hi>ſhakes and unſettles</hi> them, by bringing them to <hi>call in queſtion, received and knovvn truths;</hi> ſuch <hi>truths</hi> as they have by clear evidence been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly convinced of. A practiſe which this <hi>ſubtile Sophiſter</hi> never made more uſe of then in this age,
<note place="margin">Sceptiſciſme in Religion a dangerous evil</note> wherein many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are turned meer <hi>Scepticks, Queſtioniſts,</hi> queſtioning every thing, ſcarſe building upon any thing. How many <hi>truths</hi> of God (clear and evident truths) are by ſome in this age called into queſtion, (and thoſe ſome of them of very great and high concernment) which former ages ever looked upon as undoubted and unqueſtionable. Now what a ſubtile piece of <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> is this? Hereby Satan firſt renders the <hi>truths</hi> of God, and the <hi>wayes</hi> of God <hi>ſuspitious</hi> unto men, drawes a <hi>jealouſie</hi> upon them, and ſo prepares their hearts for the drinking in of many <hi>dangerous,</hi> and ſome <hi>damnable</hi> errors. In the fear of God take we heed how we give entertainment to any ſuch faithleſſe doubtings and queſtionings.</p>
            <p>Not but that Chriſtians both may and ought to deſire,
<note place="margin">How Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion received and known Truths, and how not.</note> and indeavour a further <hi>ſettlement,</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſhment,</hi> in known and received truths. And to that end they may take notice, not onely what can be ſaid for them; but what can be ſaid <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> them, that ſo they may not take things upon <hi>truſt,</hi> but may <hi>ſee with their owne eyes.</hi> But to call any of them in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113261:14"/>without ſome <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>cleare,</hi> at <hi>leaſt probable evidence,</hi> this, as it is <hi>dangerous to our ſelves,</hi> ſo is it <hi>injurious to the truth,</hi> and <hi>diſhonourable unto that God</hi> whoſe Truth it is. Which of us but would account it ſo for our ſelves, to have our <hi>names</hi> brought in queſtion, much more to have our <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> brought to the <hi>barre,</hi> meerly upon the <hi>groundleſſe informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of ſome <hi>jealous head,</hi> without any evidence at all. Take we heed therefore how we ſo deal with the <hi>truths,</hi> or <hi>wayes</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>Specially how we bring them to the <hi>Barre of mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> calling in queſtion the <hi>equity</hi> of them,
<note place="margin">Take heed of bringing Gods truths or wayes to mans barre. Ezek. 18.25.</note> the equity of Gods <hi>decrees, precepts, prohibitions, diſpenſations, providences.</hi> So did ſome of the <hi>Iewes</hi> of old, as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it upon them, Ezek. 18. <hi>Ye ſay the way of the Lord is not equall.</hi> And even ſo do ſome at this day make bold to <hi>weigh</hi> the <hi>myſteries of Heaven,</hi> viz. the <hi>decrees,</hi> and <hi>providences</hi> of God, at the <hi>beame</hi> of their owne <hi>carnall reaſon,</hi> queſtioning the <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> of them, which becauſe they cannot <hi>ſee,</hi> they will not <hi>beleeve,</hi> (the caſe of <hi>Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Socinians.</hi>) A high and dangerous <hi>preſumption,</hi> which who ſo giveth way unto, is in the direct way to be deceived. So was our firſt Parent decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the firſt, by hearkning unto Satan, queſtioning the <hi>truth</hi> or <hi>equity</hi> of a <hi>Divine prohibition. Hath God indeed ſaid?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place; the next ſtep that <hi>Satan</hi> maketh,
is from <hi>queſtioning</hi> to <hi>oppoſing;</hi> from a <hi>doubtfull interrogation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Confident op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> to a <hi>peremptory negation.</hi> Having <hi>queſtioned</hi> Gods <hi>precept,</hi> now he <hi>denies</hi> his <hi>threatning,</hi> which he doth with a great deal of <hi>confidence.</hi> Nequaquam morieminis, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſurely dye,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.4. Applied to the times.</note> or ſurely ye ſhall not dye.</hi> And is not this the method wherein Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſtill proceeds with ſuch as he <hi>ſeduceth,</hi> and draweth into Errors? Firſt he brings them to <hi>queſtion</hi> received truths, then to <hi>oppoſe</hi> them; and that not in a <hi>ſubmiſſive</hi> and humble, but in a <hi>confident</hi> and <hi>peremptory</hi> way. A property very obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in many of the <hi>Sectaries</hi> of the times. For a time they ſtand <hi>doubting,</hi> and <hi>wavering;</hi> and if partly <hi>reſolved,</hi> yet they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry their differences in judgement with ſome <hi>faire reſpective moderation,</hi> but afterwards they grow ſo <hi>confident,</hi> ſo <hi>peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> ſo <hi>violent,</hi> and that not onely in <hi>maintaining</hi> their <hi>own
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113261:15"/>opinions,</hi> and <hi>wayes,</hi> but in <hi>oppoſing,</hi> and <hi>affronting all others</hi> who are contrary minded, as if they had received ſome <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate revelation</hi> from Heaven. Now truly, <hi>ſuch confidence,</hi> at leaſt ſuch <hi>violence,</hi> doth not become <hi>humble Chriſtians:</hi> Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in points <hi>controverſall</hi> betwixt them and their brethren; and thoſe neither <hi>of,</hi> nor <hi>neer</hi> the <hi>foundation.</hi> True, were they <hi>fundamentalls, principles of Religion,</hi> now <hi>confidence,</hi> and <hi>earneſtnes</hi> do well. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, It is St. <hi>Iudes</hi> word in the fourth verſe of his Epiſtle,
<note place="margin">Iude 4.</note> 
               <hi>That ye contend earneſtly for the faith once given to the Saints.</hi> But being onely matters of <hi>order,</hi> (ſuch as moſt of the differences of the times are about) now Chriſtians though poſſibly they ſhould be in the truth, yet they may be <hi>ever earneſt and confident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In the third place, This <hi>grand deceiver,</hi> from <hi>confident oppoſition</hi> he falls to an <hi>unjuſt and foule crimination,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Vnjuſt and foule crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; charging Gods way with rigour and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy.</note> changing this <hi>way,</hi> theſe proceedings of God, both with <hi>rigour,</hi> and <hi>envy.</hi> With <hi>rigour,</hi> as if God had dealt <hi>hardly</hi> with our firſt Parents in abridging them of their <hi>liberty,</hi> not allowing them to eat of <hi>that tree,</hi> as well as the reſt. So much is inſinuated in that <hi>interrogation,</hi> v. 1. <hi>Yea; hath God indeed ſaid, ye ſhall not eat of every tree in the Garden? Interrogatio criminantis,</hi> or <hi>calumniantis.</hi> As if he had ſaid, this a very hard thing that you ſhould be ſo reſtrained, ſo abridged of your <hi>liberty.</hi> With <hi>envy;</hi> as if God had envied the <hi>happineſſe</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> ſpecially his perfection in <hi>knowledge.</hi> So he chargeth it expreſly, v. 5. <hi>for God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this the very direct courſe that <hi>Satan</hi> taketh in the deceiving of many ſimple well-meaning ſoules at this day?
<note place="margin">Applied to the times</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> to prejudice them againſt that <hi>way of God</hi> which is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ſet up in this Kingdom, and that by caſting the like <hi>foul criminations</hi> upon it, that he may thereby render it not onely <hi>ſuſpicious</hi> in their eyes,
<note place="margin">A generation of ſerpents ſtirred up to blaſpheme the Church; and way of God in this kingdom. Pſa. 140.2.</note> but <hi>Odious.</hi> To this end it is, that he hath of late ſtirred up, and ſet on work ſuch a <hi>Generation of Serpents.</hi> So I may well call them, and that without any breach of Charity. For ſure I am, (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith of his <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eg,</hi> and ſome other Whelps of that litter, his <hi>virulent</hi> and <hi>foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouthed Adverſaries,) They have ſharpned their tongues like a Serpent; Adders poyſon is under their lips.</hi> Selah. So ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113261:15"/>of ſome in his time, ſetting a <hi>Note of Admiration</hi> upon their heads, <hi>(Selah.)</hi> And truly ſo may we upon ſome in our time. When we read the <hi>writings</hi> of thoſe <hi>Shemei's and Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhakehs,</hi> whom Satan hath of late ſtirred up to <hi>revile,</hi> and <hi>blaſpheme</hi> the <hi>wayes</hi> of God, the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of God, the <hi>Church</hi> of God, the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of God, the <hi>People</hi> of God, well may we ſet a <hi>Selah</hi> upon their heads, and ſtand and <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> wonder that ever any that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, ſpecially ſuch as pretend to greater ſtrictneſſe then other of their brethren, ſhould ever dare to belch out ſuch <hi>prodigious blaſphemies,</hi> as thoſe <hi>libellous Pamphlets</hi> are ſtuffed withall.</p>
            <p>But what are the <hi>criminations</hi> of theſe <hi>accuſers of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Crimes char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the ſame with theſe of the Serpent.</note> What are the <hi>crimes</hi> which they ſo deeply charge upon that way which they apprehend to be now ſetting up in the Kingdome?</p>
            <p>Why, even the very ſame with thoſe which the <hi>Devil</hi> here putteth into the <hi>mouth</hi> of the <hi>Serpent</hi> (ſo as you may plainly ſee where they found them, and from whence they had them) viz. <hi>Rigour,</hi> and <hi>Envy.</hi> Amongſt their many foul and virulent <hi>charges,</hi> which they diſcharge upon this way, you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe two to be the chiefe and principall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Rigour;</hi> That any way,
which hath the <hi>name of God called upon it,</hi> ſhould be <hi>prohibited.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Rigour.</note> That people ſhould be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained</hi> from the <hi>profeſſing</hi> and holding forth of what <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> they pleaſe, at leaſt in what <hi>way</hi> they pleaſe; Oh this is a <hi>rigorous abridgement of their Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> ſavouring too ſtrongly of the <hi>Egyptian Task-Maſter.</hi> A thing not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſhould be <hi>tyed</hi> and <hi>fettered,</hi> and not left at Liberty, not only to <hi>think,</hi> but in matter of Religion to <hi>speak, write, profeſſe, practiſe, hold forth</hi> what it pleaſeth. Here is the great Charge.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Charge</hi> how like to that of the <hi>Old Serpents</hi> here?
<note place="margin">Paralleld with that of the Serpent.</note> even ſo like, as if it had been ſpit out of his mouth. Yea, (ſaith the Serpent) <hi>Hath God indeed ſaid, ye ſhall not eat of every Tree in the Garden?</hi> What <hi>a rigorous and injurious reſtraint</hi> is this, that they for whom all theſe Fruits were made, may not uſe them at their pleaſure? Even ſo ſaith the <hi>Spawn</hi> of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent now; <hi>Yea,</hi> hath <hi>Authority indeed ſaid, Ye ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe what Religion you pleaſe? Nor yet hold forth the true
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113261:16"/>Religion in what</hi> way <hi>you pleaſe?</hi> What <hi>a rigorous reſtraint</hi> is this? that they who were <hi>borm Free-men,</hi> ſpecially ſuch as are <hi>ſet at liberty by Chriſt,</hi> may not enjoy the uſe of this their liberty? That they for whom all the <hi>Ordinances</hi> were inſtituted and ordained, may not enjoy them, and uſe them as they ſhall think fitting. This is a thing which they know not how ſufficiently to declaime, and inveigh againſt. And thence are thoſe loud outcries of <hi>Tyrannie</hi> and <hi>Perſecution Tyrannie</hi> worſe then <hi>Prelaticall,</hi> and <hi>perſecution</hi> as bad as ever <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> was. And as they charge this way with <hi>Rigour;</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2"> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> So with <hi>Envy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Envie.</note> That ſome <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> ſhould be <hi>peculiarly appropriated</hi> to ſome particular perſons; <hi>Preaching,</hi> to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel, ſuch as are devoted and ſet a part to that worke; <hi>Adminiſtration of Cenſures and Diſcipline</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> and ſome <hi>ſelect perſons</hi> joyned with them, ſo as in the mean time the <hi>generality of the people</hi> ſhall be excluded; <hi>Private Chriſtians</hi> how great ſo ever their <hi>abilities</hi> be, yet may they not <hi>exerciſe their gifts</hi> in a <hi>publick way,</hi> to the publick edification of the Church; much leſſe may they intermeddle with the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church, What is this (ſay they) but <hi>Envy?</hi> even the <hi>height of envy.</hi> What was it that made that <hi>buſie young man</hi> to bring his complaint to <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 11.26, 27, 28.</note> that being private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>perſons out of Office,</hi> yet they <hi>prophecied?</hi> Was it not <hi>Envie?</hi> And what made the <hi>Diſciples</hi> to <hi>inhibit</hi> that man in the Goſpel, the <hi>Exerciſe of his gift</hi> in caſting out of Devils, only becauſe he did not joyne himſelf unto them? was it not, <hi>Envie?</hi> And what elſe is it (ſay they) that maketh the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters</hi> of the Church to appropriate the Office of <hi>preaching</hi> to themſelves? Surely nothing but <hi>Envie</hi> to the people. They know well enough that in caſe there were a <hi>libertie</hi> left for every one to <hi>exerciſe his gift</hi> as he pleaſed, the people would ſoon attain ſuch perfection in knowledge, as that their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers would be <hi>deſpiſed</hi> and brought into contempt. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon alſo is it, that they exclude them from intermedling in <hi>publick Adminiſtrations,</hi> in managing the buſineſſe of the Church, only to maintain their own <hi>Prelaticall dignity</hi> and <hi>pompe.</hi> Such are the ſuggeſtions which of late have fallen from the <hi>pens</hi> of ſome, and <hi>mouths</hi> of many.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113261:16"/>
            <p>But alas,
<note place="margin">Paralelled with that of the Serpent.</note> are they not again the very ſame with that of the <hi>Serpent</hi> here, which he chargeth upon God himſelf? <hi>For God doth know</hi> (ſaith the Serpent) <hi>that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes ſhall be opened, and you ſhall be as Gods.</hi> And even ſo ſay they, <hi>Miniſters</hi> know well enough that in the day there is ſuch a <hi>liberty</hi> granted as is deſired, the <hi>peoples eyes would be opened,</hi> and they would be as <hi>Gods,</hi> equall to themſelves, both in <hi>knovvledge</hi> and <hi>Authority.</hi> The <hi>Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel</hi> you ſee runs ſo punctuall and full, that me thinks the very comparing of them together ſhould be a ſufficient diſſwaſive to people, to keep them from giving any entertainment unto ſuch foul ſuggeſtions, which are (as you ſee) <hi>ſpit out of the mouth of the Old Serpent.</hi> Yet take one or two of theſe <hi>ſleights</hi> more. I will be brief in them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the fourth place; <hi>Satan</hi> caſting this <hi>Crimination,</hi>

               <note place="margin">4. New light held forth.</note> this <hi>charge</hi> upon this <hi>vvay,</hi> theſe proceedings of God with man; withall he holdeth forth unto the <hi>Woman</hi> a <hi>New-light</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, telling her that which neither ſhe nor her husband before ever heard of, giving her another reaſon and ground for that <hi>Prohibition,</hi> then ever ſhe dreamed of. <hi>God doth knovv</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that in the day ye eat thereof,
<note place="margin">Applied to the Times.</note> your eyes ſhall be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp;c.</hi> And is there not a great deal of ſuch <hi>nevv light</hi> held forth in this Kingdom at this day? Strong <hi>Doctrines</hi> Preached, Printed, Vented; ſome of which having lyen <hi>aſleep,</hi> nay <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>rotten,</hi> for more then a thouſand years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are now <hi>awakened,</hi> and <hi>revived.</hi> Others of them ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>hatched,</hi> never <hi>diſcloſed</hi> untill this preſent age. And theſe are held forth to the world as <hi>New-light,</hi> which being brought to the <hi>Teſt,</hi> upon due Examination and Tryall, will be found to have no more <hi>light</hi> in them, then was in this <hi>ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion,</hi> which the <hi>Serpent</hi> here holdeth forth to the woman. So as we may ſay of them (as that Greek <hi>Critick</hi> did of the <hi>Bow,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The name of it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified life, but the work was death</hi>) that are in name <hi>Light,</hi> but in truth <hi>Darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. In the laſt place;

<note place="margin">5. A promiſe of ſome great good.</note> Holding forth <hi>new-light</hi> to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, withall he <hi>maketh promiſe to her of ſome great good</hi> that ſhould accrue to her from following his <hi>Counſell;</hi> ſpecially of a great <hi>increaſe of knowledge,</hi> and of atchieving an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113261:17"/>and <hi>tranſcendent honour</hi> and <hi>dignity:
<note place="margin">A practiſe imitared by all Sectaries.</note> Your eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods, knovving good and evil.</hi> And is it not even ſuch <hi>ayre</hi> that the <hi>Hereſiarchs,</hi> the <hi>heads</hi> and <hi>prime</hi> leaders of all <hi>ſchiſmes</hi> and <hi>factions</hi> in the world have in all ages uſed to feed their <hi>Sectaries,</hi> their <hi>Diſciples</hi> with? In caſe they will but hearken to their <hi>counſell,</hi> and put themſelves upon the <hi>vvayes</hi> whith they hold forth unto them, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe them ſome <hi>great good</hi> that ſhall accrue unto them. In par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, hereby they ſhall come to <hi>knovv</hi> that which they never yet did, nor others do, nor can do, being out of that way. Beſides, they ſhall hereby be tranſlated to the <hi>higheſt forme of Chriſtianity,</hi> attaine to ſuch honour and perfection, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this they are not capable of. Theſe things I do but touch, being very willing to diſmiſſe this ſecond head of particulars, taken from the <hi>quality of the inſtrument</hi> which Satan here ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth uſe of, and the <hi>Arguments</hi> which he putteth into his <hi>mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſe we now to the third,
which I ſhall diſpatch with all convenient brevity;
<note place="margin">3. The Object, the Apple pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Woman, which was</note> being as willing to diſmiſſe this Text, and this <hi>ſubject,</hi> as poſſibly ſome of you would have me. In the third place then looke upon the <hi>Object;</hi> the <hi>Apple</hi> it ſelf which is here preſented to the Woman.</p>
            <p>And therein we ſhall take notice onely of three particulars. You have them all together in the beginning of the ſixth verſe of that third of <hi>Geneſis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> 1. <hi>She ſaw that it was good to eat.</hi> 2. <hi>That it vvas beautifull, pleaſant to the eyes.</hi> 3. <hi>That it vvas deſirable to make one vviſe.</hi> Each appliable to our preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. A word of each.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1. Good to eat, pleaſant, and nouriſhing.</note> It was <hi>good to eat, pleaſant,</hi> and <hi>delectable to the palate;</hi> and withall <hi>uſefull for nouriſhment.</hi> Such ſhe apprehended it to be; and ſuch (no queſtion) in truth it was. Not but that there might be, and moſt probably were, ſome other <hi>Trees</hi> in the Garden equalizing it in both theſe reſpects; As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>The tree of life;</hi> which how ever it was ſo called (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> determines it well) not <hi>effectivè,</hi> but <hi>ſignificative,</hi> not in regard of any ſuch <hi>operation,</hi> or <hi>vertue</hi> that it had, to <hi>give life,</hi> or <hi>preſerve life</hi> to Eternity, but in regard that it was a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> a <hi>Signe,</hi> and <hi>Seal</hi> of life and immortallity to man upon his <hi>obedience;</hi> Yet in all probability (as <hi>Mercer</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113261:17"/>of it) the fruit thereof was both moſt <hi>delectable,</hi> and <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritive,</hi> moſt pleaſant to the palate, and nouriſhing to the body. But yet ſuch properties there were alſo in the <hi>Tree of knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and happily the Woman apprehended more then there was.</p>
            <p>And theſe inticed the Woman the rather to taſte of it.
<note place="margin">Applied to the times.</note> And truly ſuch are the arguments that do much prevaile with many of thoſe who are drawne aſide to the imbracing of <hi>nevv vvayes,</hi> ſpecially that of the <hi>Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They apprehend a great deal of <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> a great deal of <hi>goodneſſe</hi> in that way. Much <hi>ſvveetneſſe</hi> in the <hi>Communion of Saints.</hi> Much <hi>goodneſſe</hi> both in the <hi>Perſons</hi> that go that way, and in the <hi>means</hi> which there may be had for <hi>Spirituall edification,</hi>
               <note place="margin">No ſweetneſſe in the way of ſeparation but may be injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without it.</note> and <hi>ſoul-nouriſhment.</hi> And we will not deny but it may be ſo. But withall, may there not be as much both <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe</hi> in another <hi>tree,</hi> as in this <hi>forbidden one?</hi> May not both theſe be found in ſome other <hi>way?</hi> as <hi>viz.</hi> in that <hi>one way</hi> which the Church is now holding forth in this Kingdom? As for that <hi>ſweetneſſe in the Communion of Saints</hi> (which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a true <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> that cannot but reliſh well to a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious palate;) What letteth but that it may be injoyed as well in this way, as in any other? Let but any judicious Chriſtian give me a reaſon for it, and I ſhall be ſilent. In the mean time, know we that if it be not ſo, it is the fault of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> not of the <hi>way,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Perſons,</hi> I ſhall not in any wiſe detract from their <hi>reall goodneſſe;</hi> (in this I ſhall deſire to have, and uſe as much <hi>charity,</hi> as ſome of them want.) But (if we may take the boldneſſe to move the queſtion,) where did they get that <hi>goodneſſe?</hi> Was it not in the <hi>Church</hi> of God, and under the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome?</hi> I preſume there are few, very few, that are now <hi>adopted</hi> into any of theſe <hi>new wayes, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated</hi> into any of theſe <hi>new bodies,</hi> but they will do the <hi>Church of England</hi> this right, as to acknowledge it their <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of this Church their <hi>Fathers</hi> in Chriſt, by whom they were begotten unto God. And if ſo; ſeeing this <hi>wombe bar</hi> them, why may not theſe <hi>breaſts give them ſuck?</hi> (You will not allow it, that <hi>Mothers</hi> which are able ſhould <hi>put forth their children</hi> to nurſe; What would
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113261:18"/>you think of thoſe children that ſhould put forth themſelves?) why may they not expect ſufficient nouriſhment; from thoſe meanes from which at the firſt they had their ſpirituall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But there is more <hi>full,</hi> and more <hi>liberall means,</hi> and maintenance in that way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pretence of better means no ſufficient warrant for ſeperation.</note> Should this be ſuppoſed, yet cannot this be conceived to be a ſufficient warrant for any preſently to forſake and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that Church, where God by his <hi>Providence,</hi> and <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> hath caſt them: No more then it would be for <hi>ſheepe</hi> or other cattle to break their <hi>fence;</hi> becauſe there is <hi>better feeding in the next paſture.</hi> But, as for the <hi>means</hi> which through the goodneſſe of God may be in the <hi>Church</hi> amongſt us injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, let me ſay this of them, and I will ſpeake it with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that ſuch is this <hi>paſturage,</hi> that if the <hi>ſheepe of Chriſt</hi> will but take their <hi>feed,</hi> here is enough not onely to <hi>keep</hi> them <hi>life-ward,</hi> but to <hi>feed</hi> them <hi>fat.</hi> Such are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe means, as if Chriſtians be not wanting to themſelves in the uſe of them, here is ſufficient not onely to maintaine the <hi>life of grace</hi> in them, but to make them <hi>rich in grace.</hi> But I haſten.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing which inticed the Woman in the fruit which ſhe ſaw,
<note place="margin">2. The beautifull outſide of the Apple.</note> was the <hi>faire and beautifull outſide of it, ſhe ſaw that it was pleaſant to the eyes.</hi> And ſurely is not this one thing that dayly inticeth, and carrieth away many to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of <hi>new-wayes?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with ſpecious out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides of new wayes.</note> even the <hi>faire and beautifull outſide of them.</hi> I meane, thoſe ſpecious <hi>gloſſes,</hi> thoſe goodly <hi>ſtiles,</hi> and <hi>titles</hi> which are put upon them. Never a one of them but is ſet out with ſome of them. As namely, that which is ſo common in the mouthes of ſome amongſt us, (though ſeparated from us,) viz. <hi>the Church way.</hi> A <hi>word</hi> which I muſt profeſſe (as it is impropriated to that one particular way) I cannot hear but as I do a harſh and jarring ſound, which ſets my teeth on edge; In as much as this <hi>one word</hi> ſo applied and uſed, it at once <hi>ſtrikes thorough the ſides of all the Churches of Chriſt that ever were in the Chriſtian world,</hi> as if never any of them were in a <hi>Church way</hi> till this laſt age, and now onely ſome <hi>few</hi> of them. And of like kinde are thoſe other of, <hi>Gods way</hi> and <hi>Chriſts way,</hi> and <hi>the Cauſe of God, and the Government of Chriſt, and the Godly party, and the cloſe walking people</hi> (which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113261:18"/>two latter tearms, what ever truth there may be in them, yet they do not ſo well become their own mouths.) Now theſe <hi>goodly ſtiles,</hi> and <hi>titles,</hi> and <hi>compellations,</hi> they do marvelouſly take many ſimple, and <hi>well meaning ſouls,</hi> (who (as I cannot therein blame them) would willingly be in the <hi>beſt way,</hi> with the <hi>beſt company,</hi>) ſpecially when they are on the other ſide ſet off with ſuch foule and <hi>opprobrious tearmes</hi> as are caſt upon the <hi>wayes</hi> of other Churches, and the <hi>members</hi> thereof, which are <hi>different</hi> from, or oppoſite to that way of theirs, as if they were all <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> having the <hi>marke of the beaſt upon them, oppoſers of Chriſts kingly Government,</hi> and what not? Now with this <hi>outſide</hi> are many taken, even as the <hi>Woman</hi> at firſt was with the <hi>outſide of the Apple.</hi> But alas, what a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is it to be thus taken? He that ſhould adventure to taſte of what is in an <hi>Apothecaries box,</hi> becauſe he eſpieth the name of ſome ſoveraigne <hi>Cordiall</hi> on the outſide of it, might ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times finde that ſaying to be too true, <hi>Extra remedium, intus venenum,</hi> that there is <hi>medicine without, but poyſon within.</hi> A word for the laſt, and I have done with this uſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing in the Apple which inticed the Woman,

<note place="margin">3. A ſuppoſed property in the Apple of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wiſdome to thoſe which eat it. Knowledge gained by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing new wayes oft times like that of the womans.</note> was a <hi>ſuppoſed property of making thoſe wiſe that ſhould eat of it,</hi> viz. by the augmentation of their knowledge. And ſurely ſuch a <hi>ſuppoſed property</hi> it is that wines much upon ſome, inticing them to the affecting of <hi>new wayes,</hi> becauſe thereby they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſuch an <hi>increaſe in knowledge,</hi> as in this way which we are in, they cannot expect to attaine unto. But what <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> that may be, for my own part I know not, neither can I conjecture, unleſſe it be ſuch a <hi>knowledge</hi> as the <hi>Woman</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to by eating of the Apple, a <hi>knowing of good and evill,</hi> and that not by a more <hi>excellent ſcience,</hi> but by a <hi>miſerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> from which kinde of knowledge the good Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us, and his Churches.</p>
            <p>You now ſee by what <hi>wayes</hi> and <hi>meanes</hi> the <hi>firſt Woman,</hi> this <hi>good Woman,</hi> the <hi>beſt of Women,</hi> came to be deceived. Now let not all theſe, any of theſe fall to the ground. You have heard to what <hi>end</hi> it is that they are held forth unto us in ſacred records; and that <hi>uſe</hi> let all of us make of them: loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon them as <hi>exemplary</hi> to us, to the intent that none of us ſhould be <hi>deceived as ſhe alſo was deceived.</hi> And ſo I have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113261:19"/>done with the former Branch of the Text, ſo far forth as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the <hi>weaker Sex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſe we now to the latter Branch, which informes us that the <hi>Woman</hi> was not onely <hi>deceived,</hi> but being deceived, <hi>ſhe vvas in the tranſgreſſion,</hi> that is, the <hi>cauſe</hi> and <hi>originall of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams tranſgreſſion,</hi> by whoſe meanes he was ſeduced to the ruine of himſelfe and all his poſterity.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> And was ſhe ſo? wherein may this be uſefull to the Daughters of this Mother?</p>
            <p>To this let the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelfe return the anſwer.
<note place="margin">A double leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the weaker Sex.</note> I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume you will not take it amiſſe from his hands, the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance hereof (as he applieth it) ſhould reach thoſe of that Sex a double leſſon; 1. Of <hi>Silence.</hi> 2. Of <hi>Subjection. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> not to take upon them to <hi>preach,</hi> or <hi>teach,</hi> or <hi>ſpeak in the publike. Subjection,</hi> not to <hi>uſurpe Authority over their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,</hi> but to be <hi>ſubject</hi> to them. Both theſe leſſons you have laid downe by the Apoſtle himſelfe in the two verſes next ſave one before the Text. <hi>Let the Woman learn in ſilence vvith all ſubjection: But I ſuffer not a Woman to teach, nor to uſurpe Authority over the man.</hi> And the two verſes following are (as I told you in the entrance upon the Text) <hi>reaſons</hi> and <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> for both. So much that firſt particle imports, (<hi>For.</hi>) <hi>For</hi> Adam <hi>vvas firſt formed, then</hi> Eve. <hi>And</hi> Adam <hi>vvas not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived but the Woman,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Woman, Poſterior in ordine, prior in culpâ</hi> (ſaith <hi>Primaſius</hi> upon it) ſhe was <hi>laſt</hi> in <hi>order,</hi> but <hi>firſt</hi> in <hi>Error.</hi> For this <hi>double reaſon</hi> muſt ſhe learn this <hi>double leſſon,</hi> viz. to <hi>learne in ſilence, and be in Subjection.</hi> I ſhall look upon each, as ſtanding in reference to the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1. Woman muſt learn in ſilence.</note> In the firſt place, <hi>Women muſt be ſilent, viz.</hi> In the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Congregations:</hi> where they muſt hear, and learn in ſilence, not taking upon them the exerciſe of any <hi>office,</hi> or <hi>gift</hi> in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. So are we to underſtand the Apoſtles <hi>injunction,</hi> and <hi>inhibition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not as if <hi>women</hi> were hereby interdicted,
<note place="margin">Women not forbidden to read, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Rhem. Annot.</hi> in 1 Tim. 2.12.</note> and prohibited either to <hi>read</hi> the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or to confer of them. So it ſeemeth the <hi>Doctors of Rhemes</hi> would fain have it, whoſe note upon the 12. <hi>verſe</hi> of this <hi>Chapter</hi> runs thus, <hi>In times of Licentiouſneſſe, Liberty, and Hereſie, women are much given to reading, diſputing, chatting, and jangling of the holy Scriptures</hi> (that is their Language) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> An impious gloſſe. A ſenſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113261:19"/>which never came into the Apoſtles thoughts, to forbid any, whether <hi>men,</hi> or <hi>women,</hi> the <hi>reading,</hi> or <hi>talking</hi> of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; which ſo it be done with <hi>modeſty,</hi> and <hi>ſobriety,</hi> with a deſire to benefit themſelves or others, is not only <hi>lawfull,</hi> but <hi>commendable.</hi> A thing which <hi>Jerome</hi> in his time, (as Doctor <hi>Fulk</hi> tells thoſe his adverſaries) highly commended in many vertuous and godly women. Amongſt others, he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth one <hi>Laeta</hi> a godly <hi>Matron,</hi> that ſhe would <hi>ſeaſon the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der tongue of her young daughter with godly Pſalmes.</hi> This women may do; <hi>Read</hi> the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>confer</hi> of them.
<note place="margin">Nor to inſtruct their families.</note> And more then this. They may, and ought to <hi>teach,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their families,</hi> to <hi>Catechiſe children</hi> and <hi>ſervants,</hi> I, and to performe other. <hi>Family-duties</hi> with them, in caſe the <hi>huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</hi> be <hi>abſent,</hi> or not <hi>able,</hi> or not <hi>willing</hi> to diſcharge them. As for their <hi>Husbands,</hi> they may give <hi>Counſell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nor to give good Counſell to their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands. Gen. 21.12.</note> and advice unto them: Who, in caſe the Counſell be good, ought to receive it from their hands; <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt <hi>hearken</hi> to the <hi>Counſell of his wife Sarah,</hi> concerning her ſervant <hi>Hagar.</hi> More then this. They may <hi>admoniſh</hi> them, putting them in minde of their <hi>duties,</hi> I, and of their <hi>faults</hi> too ſometimes, ſo it be done not in an <hi>imperious way,</hi> but with due obſervance, and reſpective acknowledgement of duty and ſubjection. They may and ought to <hi>hold forth their light,</hi> communicate their knowledge to them, if ignorant, inſtructing them in the wayes of God, that they may bring them home unto Chriſt; or if brought home, that they may further build them up.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.16. 1 Pet. 3.1.</note> How elſe ſhould the <hi>believing wife ſave her unbelieving husband,</hi> (as <hi>Paul</hi> giveth her hopes of it) but by her <hi>godly converſation,</hi> and <hi>wiſe Inſtruction?</hi> This they may do to their <hi>Husbands,</hi> and this they may do to others. And that not onely to thoſe of the <hi>ſame Sex</hi> (as <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of <hi>Matrons,</hi> that they ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Nor to inſtruct others in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare way. Tit. 2.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Teachers of good things: viz.</hi> To <hi>young Women.</hi> So it followeth. <hi>That they may teach the young women to be ſober</hi> (or <hi>wiſe</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which they were to do both by <hi>example,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> alſo, as occaſion was offered) But to <hi>Men</hi> alſo, in a private way. Thus did <hi>Briſcilla</hi> communicate her knowledge in the way of Chriſt unto <hi>Apollo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who was then (though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe a learned man) a novice and new beginner in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113261:20"/>Shee and her Husband <hi>Aquila expounded unto him the way of God more perfectly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 18.26.</note> But this they did in a <hi>private way.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>They took him unto them.</hi> And thus indeed <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> may <hi>teach</hi> and inſtruct others, both <hi>Women,</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating the knowledge which God hath given them, in a <hi>private way.</hi> Wherein God is pleaſed ſometimes to own and bleſſe their indeavours, making them effectuall for the <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of ſome, and <hi>confirming</hi> and building up of others. <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius à Lapide</hi> writing upon the 12. <hi>verſe</hi> of this Chapter, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth diverſe inſtances for it, wherewith I ſhall not trouble you. All this <hi>Women</hi> may do.</p>
            <p>But to <hi>teach publickly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">But to teach publickly.</note> or to exerciſe any <hi>publick Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration</hi> in the Church, this they may not do. This (as it ſeemeth) ſome in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time began to do. Some being indued with extraordinary gifts, as of <hi>Propheſie,</hi> &amp;c. (as we read of <hi>Philip the Evangeliſts four daughters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act, 21.9.</note> all <hi>Propheteſſes</hi>) they took upon them to ſpeak in the publick Congregations: And herein (as <hi>Eſtius</hi> conjectures) they might poſſibly be imitated and followed by ſome others. A like practiſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto hath been taken up by ſome of that <hi>Sex</hi> in after Ages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> amongſt his Hereſies,
<note place="margin">Epiphan: Haer: 49. The Error of the Quintillian in admitting women to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. <hi>Vide Danaeum de Haeres.</hi>
               </note> tells us of a certain <hi>Sect</hi> known by the name of <hi>Quintilliani</hi> (ſo called from one <hi>Quintilla</hi> a pretended <hi>Propheteſſe</hi>) who in honour of their great <hi>Grandmother Eve,</hi> and of that act of hers in <hi>eating of the forbidden fruit</hi> (which they highly magnified, as being the <hi>moſt beneficiall act</hi> to her poſterity that ever was, in as much as it made way for the <hi>bringing a Saviour into the world;</hi> directly contrary to this of the Apoſtle, who here cenſures it for a <hi>high and heinous Tranſgreſſion</hi>) they would have <hi>women</hi> admitted to the Miniſterie, to be <hi>Presbyterae,</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopae, ſhee-Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>ſhee-Biſhops,</hi> allowing them not only to <hi>Preach,</hi> but alſo to <hi>Adminiſter the Sacraments.</hi> The latter of theſe it hath been, and yet is permitted by the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> viz. <hi>That Women may in caſe of a pretended neceſſity, adminiſter a Church Sacrament,</hi> the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ſhall not need to tell it you, how the former hath been of late time practiſed by ſome of that Sex. Inſtance in that notorious Miſtris <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> who under a colourable pretext of repeating of Sermons, held a <hi>weekly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113261:20"/>Exerciſe,</hi> whereby in a little time ſhe had impoyſoned a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of that <hi>Plantation</hi> with moſt dangerous and deteſtable, deſperate and damnable <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Hereſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this it is that the Apoſtle here interdicts and prohibits: inforcing his <hi>Inhibition</hi> with this Argument in the Text,
<note place="margin">The woman for ever ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended from the exerciſe of any office or gift in the Church.</note> 
               <hi>The woman at the firſt being deceived, ſhe was in the tranſgreſsion.</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon her to be a <hi>Teacher</hi> at the firſt, ſhe thereby <hi>ſeduced her husband,</hi> and <hi>undid all her poſterity.</hi> From thenceforth therefore, in regard of the ill ſucceſſe of that her firſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching (as <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and ſome others after him inforce the Argument) all of that Sex are for ever <hi>ſuſpended</hi> from the exerciſe of any ſuch <hi>office,</hi> or <hi>gift</hi> in publick.
<note place="margin">Chryſoſt: Hom. 9. in 1 Tim. <hi>Cum malê ceſsit decendi mumes quod ſibi uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pavit Eva, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliquae muliercs â docendi mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere abstineant.</hi> Hening. Com. in Tex. 1 Cor. 14.34. ver. 35. Allegations for Women-Preachers, cleared. Pſal. 60.11.</note> A point wherein the Apoſtle is very preciſe, and punctuall, (as it ſeemeth the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of thoſe times required it) Writing to his <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> he giveth an expreſſe <hi>order</hi> about it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Let your Women keep ſilence in the Churches, for it is not permitted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them to ſpeake, &amp;c.</hi> And in the <hi>ver.</hi> following: <hi>It is a ſhame for women to ſpeak in the Church.</hi> A ſhame, becauſe not onely againſt a <hi>poſitive Lavv,</hi> but againſt the <hi>order of nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Henceforth then no more <hi>Women Preachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> No, (it may be ſaid) What ſay we then to that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Pſal. 68.11? where he maketh mention of <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Preachers, The Lord gave the word, great was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Preachers.</hi> In the Originall, the word is <hi>feminine</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Annunciatricum,</hi> as <hi>Montanus</hi> renders it) <hi>ſhee-Preachers, Women-Evangeliſts, publiſhers of glad tidings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this let Mr. <hi>Aynſvvorth</hi> returne the Anſwer, who will tell us, that however the <hi>vvord</hi> there be <hi>Feminine,</hi> yet the <hi>ſenſe</hi> is <hi>Maſculine,</hi> and is to be underſtood of <hi>men,</hi> as both the <hi>Chalde</hi> and <hi>Septuagint</hi> there render it; for which he giveth ſome parallel inſtances of like nature. But, take the word <hi>literally</hi> and ſtrictly, then it is to be underſtood only of ſuch <hi>Women</hi> as were wont to <hi>ſing ſongs</hi> unto God after the obtaining of any great Victory, or <hi>publick Deliverance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 15.20. Iudg. 5.1. 1 Sam. 18.6.7.</note> which was uſuall for women then to do: As we may ſee in <hi>Miriam,</hi> Exod. 15. and <hi>Deborah,</hi> Judg. 5. and the <hi>Women of Iſrael,</hi> who came out to meet <hi>King Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> after the ſlaughter of the <hi>Philistines,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. No warrant then for <hi>Women-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113261:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Why, but was not <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Deborah,</hi> and <hi>Hul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> and ſome others which we read of, <hi>Women Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> True, they were ſo, but that was <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and therefore ought not to be drawn into <hi>preſident,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in Rhem. 1 Tim. 2.12.</note> unleſſe it be in <hi>extraordinary Caſes.</hi> In which caſes (as Doctor <hi>Fulks</hi> tells his adverſaries of <hi>Rhemes</hi>) <hi>God hath ſometimes made uſe of Women as publick instruments of great ſervice to the Church, even for the converting of great Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Why, but <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſeemeth to give allowance to ſuch <hi>Women-Preachers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.5. explained.</note> and that in an ordinary way, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. where he tels his <hi>Corinthians</hi> that <hi>every woman which prayeth or prophecieth with her head uncovered, diſhonoureth her head.</hi> So that it ſeemeth he did not diſallow the <hi>practiſe,</hi> though he condemned the <hi>manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this it is variouſly anſwered. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi> and P. <hi>Martyr</hi>) there takes occaſion onely to cenſure the <hi>manner,</hi> yet not giving any allowance to the <hi>practiſe</hi> it ſelf, which afterwards he expreſly forbids. Others conceive that here he ſpeaks of <hi>private praying and prophecying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.24.</note> not in the <hi>Church,</hi> but at <hi>home:</hi> Others that he ſpeaks only of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being <hi>preſent</hi> at the publick prayer, and prophecy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by others. Others that he ſpeaketh there of ſuch as were inſpired with an <hi>extraordinary ſpirit of Prayer and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy.</hi> So the <hi>Ancients</hi> generally carry it. And that ſeemeth to be the moſt probable. Sure we are that in an ordinary courſe the Apoſtles <hi>prohibition</hi> is expreſle, <hi>Women may not teach in publick.</hi> And were there no other <hi>Reaſon</hi> for it, this alone might be ſufficient to <hi>ſilence</hi> them. The <hi>woman</hi> by her taking upon her to teach at the firſt, became the <hi>Inſtrument of Seduction,</hi> and <hi>Author of Tranſgreſſion</hi> to her <hi>husband,</hi> and conſequently of <hi>ruine</hi> to him and all his poſterity. Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth then no more <hi>Women-Preachers.</hi> A point wherein Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Calvin</hi> ſeemeth to be very zealous, and earneſt, averring this,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quaerc calum quodammodo terrae miſcebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſi docendi jus accipiant mulieres.</hi> Calv. in v. 12.</note> for <hi>women</hi> to take upon them the <hi>office of Teaching,</hi> to be no leſſe then a <hi>mingling of Heaven and earth together,</hi> an inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the courſe and order of nature. But for my ſelf I ſhall ſpare my <hi>heat</hi> in this cauſe, not knowing whom to ſpend it upon, in or belonging to this place. If any ſuch there be, I ſhall ſay no more but, <hi>Partem aliquam ventireferatis ad aures.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113261:21"/>
            <p>I wiſh this truth might finde ſome conveyance to their ears and hearts.</p>
            <p>Paſſe we to the ſecond of theſe Leſſons, which is,
<note place="margin">Women muſt be in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> that <hi>women ſhould be in ſubjection,</hi> not <hi>uſurping Authority,</hi> but <hi>ſubmitting</hi> to it, and that whether <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> or <hi>Civill:</hi> not taking themſelves exempt from either. True indeed, in ſome caſes they are exempt from ſome <hi>formall obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> (as of late they were from the <hi>Nationall Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi>) which <hi>Men</hi> are ingaged in. Yet are they never the more exempt from <hi>Obedience,</hi> to which, though they be not <hi>formally,</hi> yet they are <hi>vertually</hi> bound. Even as it was in <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> the <hi>Females were Circumciſed in the Males.</hi> So may I ſay of <hi>Obligations</hi> of this nature; and particularly of this late <hi>Covenant.</hi> The <hi>Females Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted in the Males, Women</hi> in their <hi>Husbands,</hi> to whom I am ſure they ought to be <hi>ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is the <hi>ſubjection</hi> which the Apoſtle here principally aymes at, (though not excluding other.)
<note place="margin">Not uſurping Authority. <hi>Mulíer naturâ (hoc eſt ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riá Dei lege) ad parendum nata eſt.</hi> Calv. in 1 Tim. 2. v. 11. 1 Cor. 14.34. Gen. 3.16. Not Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. A Woman Head of the Church; A Popiſh Cavill againſt Queen Elizabeth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed. <hi>Eſtius,</hi> in 1 Tim. 2.12. <hi>Monſtrum bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum!</hi> Corn. â Lap. ibid.</note> So he explains himſelf in the twelfth verſe of the Chapter, <hi>I ſuffer not a Woman to teach, nor to uſurpe Authority over the Man.</hi> Not to uſurpe <hi>Authority</hi> in what kinde ſoever. All ſuch uſurpation (ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi>) is againſt the <hi>Law of nature,</hi> in as much as the <hi>Woman</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>Ad parendum nata eſt,</hi> was <hi>made to obey.</hi> Which is no more then what the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelf ſaith in that forenamed place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. where ſpeaking of <hi>Women</hi> he tells us, that <hi>They are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be under Obedience, as alſo ſaith the Law:</hi> They may not then <hi>uſurpe Authority.</hi> Not <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> No? (ſay our Adverſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi>) Why then did you allow a <hi>woman</hi> to be the <hi>head of your Church?</hi> It is an obvious blot. <hi>Romiſh Commentators</hi> writing upon this of the Apoſtle, cannot miſſe it. <hi>Eſtius</hi> and <hi>Cornelius â Lapide</hi> both hit it. What, (ſaith the latter) may not a <hi>Woman teach in the Church?</hi> Much leſſe may ſhe <hi>Rule</hi> it. And if neither <hi>Teach</hi> nor <hi>Rule,</hi> How is it then that a <hi>Woman</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Head of a Church?</hi> This they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113261:22"/>againſt as a moſt prodigious and unheard of <hi>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biſhop Iewels, Defence of the Apolog. part 6 cap. 11. diviſ. 1.</note> To this let our renowned Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> return them an Anſwer, (as he hath done to their Mr. <hi>Harding,</hi> taking up the ſame Quarrell) who will tell them, that as for this <hi>Title</hi> ſo much exclaimed againſt, be it what it will.
<note place="margin">Statute Anno 26. Hen. 8. c. 1: Stows Chron.</note> 1. <hi>We deviſed it not.</hi> The device was their own, their <hi>Forefathers,</hi> even the <hi>Romiſh Clergyes in their Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> who firſt beſtowed this ſtrange ſtile upon that Famous Prince, King <hi>Henry the Eight,</hi> and that (as it may be probably conjectured) purpoſely to bring him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the talk and ſlander of the world. 2. <hi>Our Princes uſe it not.</hi> 3. <hi>They claim it not.</hi> However (as he chargeth it upon his Adverſarie) their <hi>Queen Mary</hi> did both, both own it, and uſe it; yet <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> did neither. No more do her Succeſſours. To be the <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> (or a Church) in propriety of ſpeech, is a title peculiar only unto <hi>Christ,</hi> whoſe <hi>Body</hi> the Church is. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (however, (as he ſaith) it may alſo in ſober meaning and good ſenſe be ſometimes applied to ſome <hi>principall member,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Videntur mihi iſtae mulieres caput fuiſſe Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae quae illic erat.</hi> Chryſoſt in Epiſt. ad Philip. Hom. 13.</note> or <hi>members</hi> of a Church, as he brings in <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> ſpeaking of ſome <hi>Women at Phillippi,</hi> and calling them the <hi>Head of the Church</hi> there, yet) in a proper ſenſe, it cannot be challenged by any <hi>Man,</hi> much leſſe <hi>Woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who whether ſhe may be the <hi>Head of a Civill State,</hi> or no, ſome have made it a Queſtion. <hi>Calvin,</hi> being (as I Conjecture) ſeaſoned with the principles of the <hi>Salique Law</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> which forbiddeth a <hi>Woman to inherit the Crown</hi> in that Kingdom,
<note place="margin">Whether a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may be the Head of a civill State.</note> ſeemeth to be ſomewhat earneſt againſt it. But who ſo readeth but the ſtories of <hi>Iſraels Deborah,</hi> and <hi>Englands Elizabeth,</hi> may ſee by experience that a Kingdom may flouriſh, and be happy under ſuch a Government.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>omnes prudentes ſemper inſtar portenti repudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arunt.</hi> Calv. in 1. Tim. 2. v. 11</note> Neither is this to be looked upon as any <hi>inverting of the roder of Nature</hi> for a <hi>Princeſſe</hi> to wear the <hi>Crown</hi> to which ſhe is <hi>born,</hi> and to Rule over her <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> more then for the <hi>Miſtreſſe of a Family</hi> to rule over her <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants.</hi> This the Woman may do, in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113261:22"/>as much as God hath made them ſubject to her, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently can be no uſurpation.</p>
            <p>But to <hi>uſurpe Authority over the man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Women may not uſurp Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over their husbands, but muſt be ſubject. 1 Pet. 3.1. Eph. 5.22. Col. 3.18.</note> over her <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> this the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> will by no means allow. In this caſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of neceſſity ſhe muſt be ſubject. Yee Wives</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Peter) be in ſubjection to your own Husbands,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.1. <hi>Wives ſubmit your ſelves to your own Husbands,</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) Eph. 5.22. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated again, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> And great <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſhould be ſo. This being the <hi>Law of the creation,</hi> that the <hi>Woman</hi> who was made <hi>after</hi> the <hi>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Law of the womans creation. A penalty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon the woman for ſeducing the man; viz. ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter obedience. <hi>Minus liberalis conditio paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. Calv.</hi> in Text. Gen. 3.16.</note> and <hi>for</hi> the <hi>man,</hi> ſhould be ſubject to him; Seconded with a <hi>penalty</hi> inflicted upon her, upon her <hi>defection</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that ill office which ſhe did unto him at the firſt in <hi>ſeducing</hi> him. <hi>Being deceived</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>ſhe was in the Tranſgreſſion.</hi> Hereupon ſhe is injoyned, (though ſtill as <hi>free</hi> and <hi>ingenuous,</hi> yet) a <hi>ſtricter</hi> kinde of <hi>ſubjection,</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> then formerly. Henceforth, (ſaith the Lord to the Woman, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.) <hi>Thy deſire ſhall be ſubject to thy Husband, and he ſhall Rule over thee.</hi> Why, did he not ſo before? Yes, but now his <hi>Patent</hi> was <hi>inlarged,</hi> and her <hi>liberty</hi> ſomewhat <hi>abridged.</hi> And it was but Reaſon (ſaith M. <hi>Calvin</hi>) that it ſhould be ſo; that ſhe who had given ſuch <hi>pernicious Councell</hi> to her Husband,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cato.</hi> ibid.</note> ſhould ever after be <hi>under his Government;</hi> that ſhe who had been the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to withdraw her Husband from his Allegiance to his God, ſhould thereupon forfeit her own <hi>liberty,</hi> which accordingly ſhe did, and that both for her <hi>ſelf,</hi> and all her <hi>poſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Point</hi> not unuſefull to be conſidered,
<note place="margin">A Leſſon for high and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Sex.</note> and ſometimes ſeriouſly thought of by <hi>all of that Sex,</hi> ſpecially ſuch as are of ſuch <hi>high</hi> and <hi>imperious spirits</hi> (if there be any ſuch here, let them take it home with them) as if they were made only to <hi>Rule,</hi> not at all to <hi>obey.</hi> Their ſpirits will not ſtoop to any kinde of <hi>ſubjection,</hi> ſpecially to their Husbands, (whom it may be) they look upon as <hi>Michal</hi> did upon her Husband <hi>David</hi> when ſhe ſaw him dancing
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.16.</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113261:23"/>before the <hi>Arke, dispiſing them in their hearts;</hi> No, they are reſolved they will have their <hi>wills.</hi> Let their <hi>Husbands ſay</hi> what <hi>they will,</hi> they will <hi>do</hi> what they <hi>liſt;</hi> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding their <hi>Counſels,</hi> much leſſe acknowledging their <hi>Authority.</hi> It may be they ſtick not to <hi>uſurpe Authority</hi> over them. So did <hi>Jezabel</hi> over her husband <hi>Ahab; He ruleth the Kingdom,
<note place="margin">1 King 21.8.</note> and ſhe vvill rule him,</hi> not ſticking to make bold with his <hi>name,</hi> I and with his <hi>ſignet</hi> too, ſigning what ſhe pleaſeth with it.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Spirits</hi> there have been, and ſurely yet are in ſome of that <hi>Sex.</hi> If their <hi>Husbands</hi> wear the <hi>Crown,</hi> yet they will ſway the <hi>Scepter.</hi> If their <hi>Husbands</hi> be in places of <hi>Authority,</hi> they will <hi>Rule</hi> with them, if not <hi>over</hi> them. Now as for ſuch, it will not be amiſſe for them often to reflect upon this <hi>fatall miſcarriage</hi> of their <hi>firſt Mother,</hi> which God hath purpoſely left upon record to humble them, to <hi>bring down,</hi> and <hi>keep down</hi> their <hi>spirits,</hi> that they may not be lifted up within them above what is meet; however, not ſo, as to put them upon any ſuch <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall Ambition,</hi> as to <hi>uſurpe Authority over their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,</hi> to whom they ought and muſt be ſubject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wherein the woman muſt be ſubiect to her husband.</note> But wherein <hi>ſubject?</hi> What, in all things?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not ſo. This ſubjection is not <hi>boundleſſe</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited.</hi> That were to make the <hi>man</hi> a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and the <hi>woman</hi> a <hi>ſtave,</hi> neither of which ought to be. Take the boundary therefore from the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelf in that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named place, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. where requiring <hi>wives</hi> to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to their <hi>Husbands,</hi> and giving a <hi>reaſon</hi> for it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Vt oportet,</hi> as it <hi>muſt</hi> be in regard of <hi>Gods Inſtitution;</hi> or, <hi>Vt convenit,</hi> as it is <hi>meet</hi> that it ſhould be; or, <hi>Vt decet,</hi> as it is <hi>ſeemly</hi> and <hi>comely</hi> for to be, in regard of the <hi>order of nature;</hi> withall he <hi>bounds</hi> and <hi>limits</hi> that their <hi>ſubmiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.18. In the Lord.</note> It muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the Lord, i.e.</hi> in the <hi>fear of the Lord,</hi> with an eye to his <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and <hi>in the Lord,</hi> i.e. in what ſhal be required <hi>from God,</hi> and <hi>for God,</hi> not <hi>againſt him.</hi> This is the <hi>common boundary,</hi> which bounds and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits <hi>Subjects</hi> obedience to their <hi>Prince, Childrens</hi> to their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113261:23"/>
               <hi>Parents, ſervants</hi> to their <hi>Maſters,</hi> and ſo <hi>wives</hi> to their <hi>Husbands.</hi> Shall any of them command any thing <hi>againſt God;</hi> now the rule holds, <hi>Better obey God, then man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But <hi>what if it be against Conſcience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">But what if it be againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Conſcience</hi> muſt be <hi>directed</hi> and <hi>regulated</hi> by the <hi>word,</hi> otherwiſe it is not <hi>conſcience</hi> but <hi>will,</hi> (which too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is miſtaken for <hi>conſcience</hi>) or at the beſt an <hi>erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſcience,</hi> which muſt rather be <hi>rectified</hi> then <hi>ſatisfied.</hi> In ſuch caſes where the <hi>evidence</hi> is not clear, the ſafeſt courſe is to ſubmit to this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> which I am ſure is clear, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>women ſhould be in ſubjection to their own husbands,</hi> either in <hi>doing</hi> what they <hi>require,</hi> or at leaſt in <hi>not doing</hi> what they <hi>forbid.</hi> I might here inſtance in ſome particular <hi>caſes,</hi> ſuch as the ſcruples of the times bring to hand. I ſhall only ſingle out one, and that I will but touch upon: viz. <hi>The womans forſaking of that Church whereof her husband is a member,
<note place="margin">Whether a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of her husband is a Member (it being a true Church) and joyne her ſelf to another without his conſent.</note> and joyning her ſelf by Covenant to ſome other, and that without his conſent, if not againſt his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this caſe it muſt be acknowledged, that could it be made good by clear evidence, that that <hi>Church</hi> from which this departure is made, were no <hi>true Church,</hi> but <hi>Anti-Chriſtian,</hi> now there might be ſome plea for this their <hi>Separation:</hi> But this being granted, that that Church is a <hi>true</hi> Church, ſuch a Church as wherein <hi>ſalvation</hi> may be had in an <hi>ordinary way</hi> (though poſſibly not ſo perfect as ſome other may be conceived to be) now in this caſe for the wife to <hi>deſert</hi> that Church, and to <hi>joyne</hi> her ſelf to <hi>another,</hi> ſo as they who lie in the ſame <hi>bed,</hi> and in the eye both of Gods Law and mans are both <hi>one,</hi> ſhould yet be of <hi>two Churches,</hi> it is ſuch a <hi>ſoleciſme,</hi> ſuch an <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity in Chriſtianity,</hi> as I think the world never ſaw <hi>practiſed,</hi> much leſſe heard <hi>pleaded</hi> for, untill this laſt Age. So it is, though it ſhould be with the husbands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Much more if <hi>without it;</hi> much more if <hi>against</hi> it.</p>
            <p>It is a thing which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have ever condemned as a foul errour in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that perſons who
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113261:24"/>are not <hi>ſui Juris,</hi> at their own <hi>diſpoſe,</hi> but under the command of others (as <hi>children</hi> that are under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Parents,</hi> and <hi>ſervants</hi> that are under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Maſters</hi>) ſhould ingage themſelves in any <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious</hi> vow without the conſent of their <hi>Superiours,</hi> though it be under pretext of attaining a more <hi>perfect State.</hi> And if ſo, then let it be inquired with what war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the <hi>wife,</hi> who is <hi>under ſubjection,</hi> can upon a like pretext <hi>deſert that Church,</hi> whereof her <hi>Husband</hi> is a <hi>Member</hi> (being a <hi>true Church</hi>) and <hi>ingage her ſelf by Covenant</hi> unto another, and that <hi>without</hi> his conſent, if not <hi>againſt</hi> it. Surely, if this be to <hi>ſubmit</hi> themſelves to their own <hi>Husbands,</hi> I know not what it is to <hi>uſurpe Authority</hi> over them. But I ſhall leave this, and withall the <hi>weaker Sex,</hi> to whom I have ſpoken ſomewhat more fully and largely, in as much as the <hi>Text</hi> looketh directly and principally at them.</p>
            <p>I am ingaged by promiſe to ſpeak ſomewhat alſo to the <hi>other Sex.</hi> Let me diſingage my ſelf with what brevity may be, in as much as their Leſſon from hence cometh in onely in a <hi>Collaterall</hi> way, and not ſo directly as the former.</p>
            <p>Was the <hi>woman deceived at the firſt,
<note place="margin">Application to men.</note> and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived was ſhe in the Tranſgreſſion?</hi> What uſe ſhall <hi>men</hi> make of this:</p>
            <p>Nay,

<note place="margin">1. What uſe they ſhould not make hereof.</note> rather (in the firſt place) what <hi>uſe</hi> ſhall they not make of it? It is a <hi>truth</hi> that is ſubject to be <hi>abuſed, perverted.</hi> And therefore let me firſt put in a <hi>Caveat</hi> to prevent that abuſe, which in brief is this.</p>
            <p>Let not this be taken up in a <hi>contumelious way</hi> to the <hi>diſparagement of the Sex.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not take up this firſt infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in a way of diſparagement to the Sex.</note> Let not any of the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> take occaſion from hence to <hi>diſdain</hi> or <hi>undervalue</hi> the <hi>daughters of Eve,</hi> ſo as to diſreſpect their <hi>perſons,</hi> or deſpiſe their <hi>counſels.</hi> Holy <hi>Iob</hi> durſt not <hi>despiſe the cauſe of his man-ſervant or maid-ſervant when they contended with him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 31.13.</note> Far be it from <hi>Husbands</hi> then to <hi>despiſe the counſels of their Wives,</hi> becauſe of their <hi>Sex.</hi> The Story
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113261:24"/>tells us in that two and twentieth chapter of the ſecond Book of <hi>Kings,</hi> how <hi>Hilkiah the chief Prieſt,
<note place="margin">2 King. 22.14.</note> and Shaphan the Scribe,</hi> and divers other <hi>eminent perſonages,</hi> by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> addreſſed themſelves to a <hi>woman, viz. Huldah</hi> the <hi>Propheteſſe,</hi> to conſult with her in a <hi>matter of Religion,</hi> touching the <hi>Book of the Law</hi> which was found in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and to enquire what courſe they ſhould take for the <hi>expiating</hi> of thoſe many and great <hi>Violations of that Law,</hi> the guilt whereof then lay upon the Land. And in the ſecond of <hi>Samuel,</hi> cap. 20. we read how <hi>Joab</hi> that great <hi>Commander</hi> diſdained not to hearken to the Counſell of a <hi>Woman at Abel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 20.19.20.</note> as did alſo the reſt of the <hi>Citizens</hi> there. <hi>Good Counſell</hi> ought not to be rejected from what <hi>hand</hi> ſoever it cometh, much leſſe becauſe from the hand of a <hi>Woman.</hi> True, the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man vvas deceived</hi> at the firſt, and by her counſell was a means to deceive her <hi>Husband.</hi> That firſt Counſell ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ill, &amp; proved <hi>Deſtructive</hi> to him that hearkned to it. But what then? Muſt her Counſell therefore no more be hearkned to? Not ſo. Let not this firſt miſcariage be remembred in ſuch a way, or yet in any way that may be to the <hi>prejudice</hi> or <hi>diſparagement</hi> of the Sex.</p>
            <p>No reaſon for it.
<note place="margin">The Woman repaired in point of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by Chriſt himſelf.</note> In as much as <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf hath ſufficiently <hi>repaired and reſtored that Sex in point of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> This he did in the dayes of his <hi>fleſh,</hi> in ſhewing many tokens of <hi>ſpeciall grace</hi> and favour to ſome of that <hi>Sex.</hi> But more ſully after his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing firſt unto them. Therein did he apply a <hi>Salve</hi> to this firſt <hi>Soar,</hi> and that a very proper one, ſalving, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſcar and blemiſh of that <hi>firſt infirmity,</hi> as may appear in ſome particulars. 1.
<note place="margin">Matth. 28.9.10. Ioh. 20.11. &amp;c.</note> Did <hi>Satan appear and ſpeak firſt to the Woman?</hi> So did Chriſt after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection <hi>firſt appear,</hi> and reveal himſelf to the <hi>Woman.</hi> 2. Was the Woman <hi>firſt deceived</hi> by Satans Suggeſtions? So was the <hi>Woman</hi> here <hi>firſt undeceived,</hi> as touching the myſteries of Chriſts <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and that by his own <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:113261:25"/>3. Was the <hi>Woman</hi> made the <hi>Inſtrument to deceive the man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lo here the <hi>woman</hi> made an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to <hi>undeceive the man,</hi> to undeceive even the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, who (as it ſeemeth) were in a great meaſure miſtaken about the <hi>Myſtery of the Reſurrection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.9.</note> untill ſuch time as they had received it from the <hi>Women,</hi> who had been <hi>eye</hi> and <hi>ear Witneſſes</hi> of it. Such honour did <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf put upon this <hi>Sex;</hi> making thoſe <hi>vvomen</hi> (as <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith elegant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>Apoſtolorum Apoſtolas,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerom:</hi> Prolog: in Zephan:</note> Apoſteleſſes to the very A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves.</hi> Let not then this <hi>old ſore,</hi> which is ſo fairly and thorowly <hi>healed</hi> be ever <hi>rubbed</hi> upon again in any ſuch a way to the <hi>contumelious disparagement</hi> of the Sex. This being promiſed by way of <hi>Caution;</hi> Let me now ſhew you what <hi>uſe men</hi> may, and ought to make of this <hi>infirmity</hi> in that Sex.</p>
            <p>Or rather let Saint <hi>Peter</hi> do it for me,
<note place="margin">What uſe men may and ought to make of this firſt infirmity in the woman.</note> who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized the ſum of all that I ſhall ſay in a few words, in the former part of one verſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. Where ſpeaking of <hi>Conjugall duties,</hi> he willeth <hi>husbands</hi> to <hi>dvvell vvith their vvives, according to knovvledge, giving honour to them as being the vveaker veſſels.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.7.</note> Marke it. Such is the <hi>Woman,</hi> in courſe of nature, the <hi>vveaker Veſſell,</hi> weaker then the <hi>man,</hi> and that both in <hi>body</hi> and <hi>minde.</hi> And being ſo, in regard of this her <hi>naturall infirmity,</hi> ſhe challengeth from the <hi>man</hi> a threefold reſpect:
<note place="margin">A threefold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to be yielded to the woman in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard hereof.</note> 1. That he muſt <hi>dvvell vvith her.</hi> 2. Dwell with her <hi>according to knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> and 3. <hi>Give honour to her:</hi> A word of each.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Dwell with her.</hi> This reſpect do <hi>Husbands</hi> owe to their <hi>Wives,
<note place="margin">1. Cohabitation.</note> Cohabitation,</hi> ſo as not to <hi>eſtrange</hi> or <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> themſelves from them without juſt and neceſſary occaſion. In all probability had <hi>Adam</hi> been preſent with his <hi>Wife,</hi> Satan would not have <hi>ſet upon her,</hi> or if he had, yet ſhe had not been ſo <hi>deceived</hi> as ſhe was.</p>
            <p>The <hi>unneceſſary abſence</hi> of Husbands from their Wives oft times expoſeth them to many <hi>dangerous temptations,</hi> which otherwiſe might either be <hi>prevented</hi> or <hi>fruſtrated.</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:113261:25"/>Which let it be taken notice of by thoſe <hi>ill husbands</hi> (ſo I may call them in more reſpects then one) who care not how little they are within their <hi>owne doores:</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Leſſon for ill Husbands who love not their own homes.</note> There <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe</hi> (it may be) is better to them then their own. Nay poſſibly, they can ſpend whole <hi>dayes,</hi> it may be <hi>nights</hi> too, in the <hi>Taverne,</hi> in the <hi>Ale houſe, Gaming,</hi> and <hi>Drinking</hi> (if not worſe,) whilſt in the meane time they leave their <hi>wives penſive,</hi> and <hi>diſcontented</hi> at home. Little do ſuch regard, or conſider what <hi>temptations</hi> thoſe <hi>weaker veſſels</hi> are hereby expoſed to. Which if they did, and withall bare any true affection to them, they would not give way to ſuch <hi>unneceſſary eſtrangements.</hi> Here is the firſt of theſe duties, <hi>Cohabitation. Husbands</hi> muſt therefore <hi>dwell with their Wives</hi> (ſo far forth as the <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> will permit) becauſe the <hi>weaker veſſels.</hi> Being ſo <hi>weak</hi> ſo <hi>infirme,</hi> and ſo <hi>apt to be deceived,</hi> it is not good that they ſhould be leſt two much <hi>alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Dwell with them according to knowledge.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
Scienter, prudenter. <hi>Knowingly, diſcreetly, wiſely.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. A wiſe carriage towards her.</note> The more <hi>weake</hi> the <hi>Woman</hi> is, the more <hi>wiſe</hi> the <hi>man</hi> had need to be, that ſo he may ſet his <hi>wiſdom</hi> againſt her <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Exerciſing his wiſdome ſpecially in theſe foure par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In bearing with her weakneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Manifeſted in 4. particulars.</note> This reſpect all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> owe one unto another;
<hi>We that are ſtrong</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ought to bear the infirmities of the weak.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. In bearingwith her weakneſſe. Rom. 15.1.</note> Much more <hi>Husbands</hi> to their <hi>Wives.</hi> So long as they are <hi>infirmities,</hi> bear them. I, though there ſhould be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>more</hi> in them; yet be contented to <hi>bear much.</hi> It will be a point of <hi>wiſdom</hi> ſo to do, and that in more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards then one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Bearing their infirmities, <hi>help them.</hi>
It is one office which the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Helping her infirmity. Rom. 8.26.</note> performeth unto all that are <hi>Eſpouſed</hi> to him; It <hi>helpeth their infirmities,</hi> Rom. 8. And this office ſhould Husbands perform to their <hi>Wives.</hi> Do what in them lyeth to <hi>help their infirmities. Help</hi> them, and that (as <hi>Phyſitians</hi> do the <hi>Infirmities</hi> of their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,</hi>)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113261:26"/>firſt in a way of <hi>Prevention;</hi> then of <hi>Cure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">In a way of Prevention.</note> 
               <hi>By way of Prevention,</hi> doing what they may to keep them <hi>from falling,</hi> from being <hi>Deceived.</hi> To that end <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> them, <hi>going before</hi> them in a holy, and Religious <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample:</hi> then <hi>ſtaying</hi> them, by ſuggeſting to them ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Counſels</hi> and <hi>Admonitions,</hi> and thoſe ſo <hi>qualified,</hi> ſo mixed, and tempered with <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ſvveetneſſe,</hi> as that they may not be rendered <hi>diſtaſtefull</hi> to them. In ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alſo uſing gentler, or ſtronger <hi>Revulſions,</hi> or <hi>reſtraints,</hi> as neceſſity requireth.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">By way of Cure.</note> 
               <hi>By vvay of Cure.</hi> In caſe they be <hi>fallen,</hi> now ſeek the <hi>raiſing,</hi> and <hi>restoring</hi> of them; Which muſt be done in a <hi>Spirit of meeknes.</hi> This <hi>Paul</hi> requires from all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians towards their <hi>Brethren. If any man bee overtaken in a fault,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> yee vvhich are ſpirituall reſtore ſuch a one in the Spirit of Meekeneſſe,</hi> Gal. 6. Even as it is with <hi>bones,</hi> which are broken,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ab <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>quod apud medicos uſurpatur pro luxata membra in ſuum locum reſtituere,</hi> Vid. Scap. &amp; Steph.</note> or <hi>dis joynted,</hi> (for from hence the Metaphor there is taken, as ſome conceive it) they require a ſoft and tender hand to ſet or put them in again. So ſhould Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans deal one with another. Specially <hi>husbands</hi> with their <hi>vvives.</hi> Being <hi>bone of their bone,</hi> in caſe they be out of <hi>jont,</hi> labour to ſet them <hi>right,</hi> but let it be with all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>tenderneſſe.</hi> In caſe they be deceived, ſeek to <hi>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.23.</note> but let it be with all <hi>lenity</hi> and <hi>gentlenes.</hi> Thus the Apoſtle requires <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhould deale with their <hi>deceived people; In meeknes inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25. 3. Not feeding their follies. <hi>Et ſanè multae ineptiae maritis ferende ſunt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voxanda multa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caedia, &amp; ſimul cavendum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſuâ indulgentiâ ſtultitiam fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veant.</hi> Calv. in 1 Pet. 3.7.</note> if peradventure God vvill give them Repentance.</hi> And ſo let <hi>Husbands</hi> deal with their <hi>deceived vvives.</hi> Thus <hi>Bearing,</hi> thus <hi>Helping</hi> their <hi>Infirmities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (in the third place) ſo <hi>bearing,</hi> and ſo <hi>helping them,</hi> as that yet they may not nouriſh them. It is <hi>Calvins</hi> caveat upon that Text of Saint <hi>Peter; Let Husbands bear vvith their vvives vveakneſſes, yet ſo as they doe not feede their follies.</hi> Such <hi>indulgence</hi> is no waies allowable, as not in <hi>Parents</hi> towards their <hi>children,</hi> ſo nor in <hi>Husbands</hi> towards their <hi>Wives.</hi> In this reſpect <hi>Husbands</hi> muſt dwell with their wives according to <hi>wiſedome,</hi> one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113261:26"/>whereof is ſo to tolerate evils, as not to <hi>foment</hi> and <hi>cheriſh</hi> them.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
In the laſt place;
<note place="margin">4. Not being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by them.</note> Taking heed of <hi>feeding their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> withall take heed of being <hi>infected</hi> with them, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by them.</hi> So was the <hi>firſt Man;</hi> and ſo was the <hi>ſtrongeſt man;</hi> and ſo was the <hi>wiſeſt man: Adam, Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Solomon,</hi> each <hi>deceived</hi> by the woman. And ſurely ſo have many been, and daily are in theſe <hi>ſeducing times,</hi> drawn aſide into <hi>Errors</hi> by like <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> even thoſe that lie in their <hi>boſomes.</hi> In this regard therefore let <hi>husbands</hi> be <hi>cautelous, dvvelling vvith their vvives as men of knovvledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A laſt reſpect due unto the <hi>Woman</hi> in regard of her <hi>weakneſſe</hi> is yet behind, of which but a word.
<note place="margin">3. Give honour to the Woman: which conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in three particulars.</note> And that is the <hi>giving honour</hi> unto her. Honour, not as from the <hi>inferior</hi> to the <hi>ſuperior;</hi> but honor as to the <hi>weaker veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</hi> Which conſiſteth chiefly in three particulars. 1. In <hi>hiding their vveak eſſe.</hi> 2. In <hi>defending them againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries.</hi> 3. In <hi>providing vvhat is meet for them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.23.</note> All theſe wayes <hi>nature</hi> teacheth us to <hi>put honour upon the leſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable parts of the bodie,</hi> as the Apoſtle telleth us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.23. And all theſe wayes both <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> ſhould teach <hi>Husbands</hi> to <hi>give honour to their Wives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>hiding their vveakneſſes,</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">Hiding her weakneſſe.</note> which in truth in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that <hi>conjugall union</hi> betwixt them, are their <hi>ovvn vveakneſſes:</hi> and therefore ought to be <hi>hid</hi> ſo far forth as may be <hi>vvithout ſin.</hi> Not <hi>divulged,</hi> and <hi>proclaimed</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, as the manner of ſome is, who do thereby but diſcover and blaze their <hi>ovvne ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Defending them againſt vvrongs and injuries;</hi>
ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being very tender of their <hi>reputations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Defending her againſt inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Matth. 1.19.</note> and <hi>good names;</hi> As <hi>Joſeph</hi> was of the Reputation of his <hi>eſpouſed Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Providing</hi> for them,
<hi>allovving them liberall and honourable maintenance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Allowing her Honorable maintenance.</note> not onely for <hi>neceſſity</hi> but for <hi>conveniency,</hi> according to their owne <hi>eſtate, degree,</hi> and <hi>quality.</hi> Remembring that they were made <hi>non in ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113261:27"/>ſed in adjutorium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſtius</hi> in 1 Pet. 3.7.</note> not to be <hi>ſlaves,</hi> or yet <hi>ſervants,</hi> but <hi>helpes, yoakefellovves;</hi> and ſo ought to be <hi>regarded, respected, honoured</hi> accordingly.</p>
            <p>And thus I have, as briefly as I could, given you the <hi>heads</hi> of ſuch <hi>duties</hi> as the <hi>Woman</hi> challengeth from the <hi>Man</hi> in regard of her <hi>originall,</hi> and <hi>naturall vveak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> And withall at length diſpatched what I proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to my ſelfe when I took this portion of Scripture in hand, which I here profeſſe, not any propenſe inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my own to <hi>Subjects of this nature</hi> (which from my heart I wiſh I might never have occaſion any more to meddle with) but the <hi>preſent neceſſity</hi> of the <hi>times</hi> and <hi>place</hi> put me upon. Let me now diſmiſſe it, and you with Prayer for a Bleſſing.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113261:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
